<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Humble advice to the conforming and non-conforming ministers and people how to behave themselves under the present liberty / by the author of Toleration not to be abused.</title>
            <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1673</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40712</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19538</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12289629</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12289629</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58860</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40712)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58860)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 890:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Humble advice to the conforming and non-conforming ministers and people how to behave themselves under the present liberty / by the author of Toleration not to be abused.</title>
                  <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 137, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Collins ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
                  <note>"A dialogue betwixt the independent and Presbyterian" has separate t.p.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 137.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[3] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58860:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58860:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>HUMBLE ADVICE TO THE CONFORMING AND NON-CONFORMING MINISTERS AND PEOPLE, How to behave themſelves under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Liberty.</p>
                  <p>By the AUTHOR of Toleration not to be abus'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>James Collins</hi> at the Kings Arms in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1673.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58860:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58860:2"/>
                  <head>ADVICE TO THE CONFORMISTS and Non-Conformiſts.</head>
                  <p>SOme, that think I have ſufficiently diſcovered both the <hi>ſin</hi> and the <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> of the preſent <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> deſire I would fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſider what may be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to offer by way of <hi>reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy:</hi> but when the <hi>foundations are out of courſe,</hi> what can I ſay or do?</p>
                  <p>Our Church now ſuffers as the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> did, by <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>prophaneneſs:</hi> and we have noted, that our Diviſions and Separations are the cauſe of <note place="margin">General.</note> the <hi>firſt,</hi> which (as I have ſhewn
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58860:3"/> in another place) can no way be fully removed, but by our <hi>reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in the publick <hi>Temple</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: as our <hi>prophaneneſs,</hi> the other great miſchief and diſeaſe of the time, by a ſpeedy, and hearty, and general <hi>reformation</hi> of life.</p>
                  <p>There is a comfort attending good <hi>endeavours,</hi> even when there is but little hope of <hi>ſucceſs:</hi> wherefore, if it be not a preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption to follow the example of one otherwiſe minded, I ſhall venture to produce my <hi>direction;</hi> and what I humbly conceive to be the <hi>preſent duty</hi> both of the <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> in order to the ſecuring the Church from total <hi>ſhipwreck</hi> in the preſent <hi>ſtorm;</hi> adding my <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition</hi> alſo, that <hi>both</hi> would lay it to <hi>heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58860:3"/>
                  <p>It is a time of <hi>liberty,</hi> and men are very apt to do what ſeemeth <hi>right in their own eyes:</hi> and I could even wiſh that they would do ſo in earneſt; if they would firſt wipe off the duſt of <hi>prejudice</hi> and <hi>paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> For I doubt not but we are generally convinced by the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,</hi> which we all profeſs, that it is indeed our <hi>duty,</hi> and <hi>intereſt</hi> too, to <hi>love one another,</hi> yea to forbear and yield to one another, yea to <hi>deny our ſelves</hi> in the little ſatisfaction of having our <hi>own wills</hi> and our own ways in ſmall and <hi>ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fferent</hi> things for the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good;</hi> and to follow <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>holineſs</hi> with a <hi>conſcience void of offence towards God and all men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But that I may be a little more <note place="margin">More par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</note> particular. I cannot believe that we indeed differ about the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell;</hi> or in our notions of true <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58860:4"/> ſome in their heats have inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated: or that our wiſeſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries think, whatever they ſay, that the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Powers</hi> and Courts are meerly <hi>merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi> or do really and intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally encourage Vice, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance ſolid and <hi>true picty:</hi> yet my hearty and humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt to them, in the firſt place, is, that they would conſider; 1. What the cauſe of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Contempt</hi> may be; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſomething be not too juſtly imputable to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> which ought not to be carefully ſearcht and <hi>reform'd</hi> before it be too <hi>late.</hi> Methinks 'tis adviceable, now you have ſo little to do with <hi>Schiſm,</hi> that you ſo turn the edge of your <hi>power</hi> againſt <hi>prophanneſs,</hi> as it may appear you are as heartily againſt <hi>this</hi> as <hi>that;</hi> and that none may think any longer,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58860:4"/> they have cauſe to leave us as <hi>enemies to God</hi> and godlineſs, and good men.</p>
                  <p>I have reaſon to affirm, that zeal was never guilty of a groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer ſlander, then by ſaying, that the <hi>preſent Clergy</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> is generally igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, <note place="margin">The Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy.</note> idle, prophane, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of godlineſs; under which guilt I heartily pray that none may die impenitent. Sure, if this zeal had any <hi>ground</hi> or <hi>love,</hi> it would be more <hi>Regular,</hi> and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Mr. <hi>Baxter's</hi> good advice, and by proper complaint and proof endeavour, at leaſt, our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> or <hi>Ejection.</hi> But 'tis too too uncharitable and groundleſs. I am confident, it is nearer to truth to ſay, that this Church hath not been bleſsed with a more Able, regular, and <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ous Clergy,</hi> theſe <hi>hundred</hi> years
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58860:5"/> (and then I might ſay a <hi>thouſand)</hi> then at preſent; which I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to <hi>flatter,</hi> but to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage my brethren to <hi>perſeverance</hi> and continuance in Well-doing, under all ſuch ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Speeches of <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> againſt them.</p>
                  <p>Yet it cannot be denied, that <note place="margin">Too many faulty.</note> the few <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Miniſters, found here and there amongſt us, are <hi>too many:</hi> and untill the power of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> both as to the <hi>Admiſſion</hi> and <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> of Miniſters be more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, and better <hi>Countenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>'d</hi> by <hi>Law,</hi> we may wiſh a through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment in this particular till our <hi>hearts ake;</hi> yet theſe ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers might know that the <hi>Church</hi> is purged of ſome ſuch notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Scandalous</hi> perſons daily, where the <hi>power</hi> of the Church <hi>can</hi> do it: and where it <hi>cannot,</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:58860:5"/> we ſhould pity, and not <hi>clamcur.</hi> Would the <hi>Patrons</hi> be pleaſed to <note place="margin">Patrons.</note> conſider their great <hi>truſt</hi> a little better, they might lay a <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of better hopes for the <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ure:</hi> and O that the <hi>Lord of the Harveſt</hi> would put it into all their hearts, not onely to diſpoſe of their gifts <hi>freely,</hi> but <hi>wiſely;</hi> and firſt to take advice with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>unconcerned</hi> perſons before they preſent their <hi>Clerks</hi> to the <hi>Biſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p;</hi> that there might be no <hi>temptation</hi> upon him to admit the <hi>unworthy</hi> for fear of a <hi>Quare im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But, my brethren, (I mean you who are not aſhamed to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Conformiſts)</hi> may not <hi>conſcience</hi> of our duty ſupply all the real or ſuppoſed defects in the <hi>Law?</hi> why ſhould any of our <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ves</hi> be a ſhame to the <hi>beſt</hi> profeſſion? why ſhould Omiſſion, male-Adminiſtration
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58860:6"/> of our <hi>Office,</hi> cauſe the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> to <hi>triumph,</hi> or <hi>blaſpheme</hi> that holy Name by which we are called, both as <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Miniſters?</hi> Do our Enemies ſtrike us in <hi>Malice,</hi> and is it not in our power to turn it to our <hi>benefit?</hi> Let the <hi>Dagger</hi> that is intended to <hi>ſtab,</hi> open our <hi>Impoſtume,</hi> and let out our <hi>Corru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Conſider your Calling,</hi> and <note place="margin">Do your whole Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</note> know that both God and man, and the Souls of your People, and the credit of Religion, and and the preſent Security of the Church of God, expects your diligence and faithfulneſs in the <hi>Duties</hi> of it; and it is but <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>caſon,</hi> your Enemies being Judges. One that is no great Friend, ſaith of us, <hi>They ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ould conſider, that</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Reflect on Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e abuſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3</note> 
                     <hi>the Declaration requires of them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſormity; and indeed it is but</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:58860:6"/> 
                     <hi>reaſonable</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that thoſe who will Conform, ſhould be exact in the doing of it.</hi> Let not the abuſe of Liberty in others wear out the Sence, or abate the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of your Office; for you know you are obliged both to be <hi>Sincere</hi> and <hi>Intire,</hi> wanting nothing, either of <hi>Inward</hi> or <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> Worſhip required at your hands: Thus you will <hi>fulfil your Miniſtry</hi> indeed; and doubt not, but <hi>Duty</hi> will ever anſwer it ſelf to God and Man, when little Arts and Devices for <hi>Siniſter ends</hi> run into the dark to hide themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Why ſhould it be ſaid, that <note place="margin">Preach better.</note> the <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> do out-<hi>preach</hi> us? Have they better <hi>Parts,</hi> or more <hi>Learning?</hi> It cannot be ſaid. Hath <hi>Uſe</hi> procured them a better <hi>Hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t,</hi> or <hi>Knack</hi> of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as they call it? I can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58860:7"/> believe it: if in any it be ſo, 'tis not generally; and where it is, let it be our <hi>ſhame:</hi> let it quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken our <hi>ſtudy and practice</hi> for our improvement. Are they <hi>affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> ſo be ye: are they <hi>practical and pious,</hi> ſo be ye. Never be aſhamed to learn good of an <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi> eſpecial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y when by that good you ſhall not onely be more effectual for the good of your people, but remove a ſcandal from your perſons and office, and the whole Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that ſuffers by ſome piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and careleſs Preachers.</p>
                  <p>Eſpecially let us conſider the <note place="margin">Mind the Rule of Preaching.</note> 
                     <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of our Preaching: the rule is the plain <hi>Word of God,</hi> and the Doctrine of it, as it lies in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our own <hi>Church.</hi> I need not tell you what advantage our Adverſaries take <note place="margin">Reflect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on p. 13.</note> from our <hi>juvenile</hi> extravagancies
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58860:7"/> in this kind: they tell us that many preach <hi>Socinianiſm,</hi> and make the <hi>practice</hi> of ſuch (moſt unreaſonably!) no ſmall <hi>reaſon</hi> of their <hi>Non-Conformity.</hi> But is it a matter of <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aiſe</hi> to us, that the <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> ſhall plead their kindneſs to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our <hi>own Church</hi> againſt us? Is it indeed <hi>our glory</hi> to uſe this <hi>liberty</hi> in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and their <hi>ſhame</hi> to uſe the like in <hi>practice?</hi> Is there no <hi>Non-Conformity</hi> in point of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine?</hi> Is it wholly contracted into the <hi>one point</hi> of <hi>Worſhip?</hi> To what end did you ſubſcribe the <hi>Articles?</hi> To what end did you promiſe otherwiſe at your <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation?</hi> When you forſake your <hi>Youth,</hi> I hope you will leave this <hi>vanity,</hi> whereby you indiſcreetly diſturb the Church, and open the mouths of <hi>gainſayers</hi> to very little purpoſe: and though it is but
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58860:8"/> your own <hi>perſonal folly</hi> to do ſo, and cannot poſſibly have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon our <hi>publick Doctrine,</hi> as weak men would fear: yet <hi>ſhall I praiſe you in this? I praiſe you not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Conſider alſo the <hi>end</hi> of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. <note place="margin">The End of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Deſign nothing ſo much in contriving and uttering your Sermons, as the <hi>ſaving your ſelves and thoſe that hear you.</hi> Preach <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>repentance,</hi> and the plain practical <hi>Catechetical</hi> points, with that ſolidneſs and zele that may commend you, not to the idle <hi>Humms,</hi> but the very <hi>Conſciences</hi> of your <hi>hearers:</hi> while with full evidence they are convinced, that you deſire their good, and deſign their <hi>happineſs;</hi> and no temptation may be left them to forſake your Miniſtry <hi>for their edification.</hi> Let nothing ſavour of Self-eſteem, Self-ſeeking, or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58860:8"/> 
                     <hi>revenge</hi> upon <hi>perſons</hi> or <hi>parties;</hi> or of flattery and connivance at ſin in any; have no jerks or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections</hi> at true <hi>piety</hi> or ſtrictneſs of life in any. Let a formal, dull, and flat ſpirit of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency in Religion be far from you; for why ſhould you <hi>preach</hi> away your people? Whatever you imagine, this is not your <hi>wiſdom; he that wins ſouls is wiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet you muſt conſider alſo, <note place="margin">Catechiſe.</note> that all your duty is not diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged when you have <hi>read prayers</hi> and <hi>preacht a Sermon;</hi> lay a <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> for the eſtabliſhment of the next (and we hope better) Age, by <hi>Catechiſing</hi> the Younger ſort, and opening the <hi>fundamental</hi> points of the Catechiſm to them. Labour to be ſerious and ſeaſonable in your Diſcourſes to the <hi>Sick;</hi> and be ready to Viſit them upon all occaſions. And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58860:9"/> take all opportunities to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance Vice,</hi> and Vanity; <note place="margin">Shame Vice.</note> and to imprint upon your Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple undoubted apprehenſions of <hi>Piety</hi> both of your <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Calling:</hi> F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r certainly, <hi>ſomething</hi> elſe ſhould ſhew us to be <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> of God, beſides our habit, eſpecially, when <hi>that</hi> is <hi>deſpiſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We pray dayly, that the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> of God may be <hi>endowed</hi> or <hi>cloathed with Righteouſneſs:</hi> It <note place="margin">Left the Church ſuffer.</note> is a <hi>Garment</hi> as well for <hi>defenſe</hi> as for <hi>Ornament,</hi> both of our Selves, and the <hi>Church</hi> of God; who uſually is wounded through the <hi>Sides,</hi> and ſuffers reproach, by the real or pretended <hi>looſneſs</hi> of her <hi>Clergy.</hi> I have reaſon to think your very Enemies know you are much ſlandered: Yet 'tis pity your <hi>Lives</hi> ſhould be other then ſuch, as no imputation can faſten upon you. The Fire
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58860:9"/> is kindled, O Lord, let the <hi>Sons of Levi be purged as Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y offer unto the Lord an offering in Righteouſneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where the <hi>Laws</hi> have deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined <note place="margin">The Laws our Rule: but Love alſo.</note> you, make them your <hi>Rule;</hi> but in <hi>other</hi> things let me beſeech you to ſhew your <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and love of Peace, and (as much as in you lieth) your <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſiveneſs</hi> to ſuch as <hi>deſpiſe</hi> and <hi>perſecute</hi> you, as our <hi>common Lord</hi> hath commanded you: For, <hi>except your Righteouſneſs exceed the Righteouſneſs of the</hi> Scribes <hi>and Phariſees, you are not worthy of the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I fear ſome of us have very needleſly ſtirred a Spirit of Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie in our Brethen againſt us theſe <hi>three</hi> ways; 1. By ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Office</hi> of <hi>Preaching.</hi> 2. By taking <hi>new methods</hi> in the uſe of that Office. 3. By ſpeaking
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58860:10"/> unwari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y in the favour of <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry:</hi> And ſeeing your <hi>Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es</hi> have object<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d them <hi>all</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, giv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me leave to take n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tice of the <hi>effence;</hi> and to ſpeak my mind <hi>fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly</hi> and <hi>plainly</hi> upon e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch of them.</p>
                  <p>For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> firſt touchi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <hi>Preach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng:</hi> I am not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rant, <note place="margin">Slight not Preaching.</note> that the <hi>Temple</hi> is called t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſe of Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ye:</hi> And I can by no means conſent with them, that <hi>compare</hi> it with, much l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m that <hi>prefer</hi> Preaching before <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I know alſo, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Matt. 28. 19.</note> had their g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eat <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to Preach, that they might teach the <hi>Nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> and convert the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel <hi>World</hi> to <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> yet the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ciples were to be taught af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, <hi>v.</hi> 20. And it cannot be deni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that they were <hi>firſt</hi> ſent to the <hi>Houſe of Iſrael;</hi> and that they accordingly Preach'd to the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58860:10"/> 
                     <hi>Jews,</hi> who were yet the <hi>Church of God:</hi> Among whom our <hi>Lord</hi> himſelf open'd the <hi>Scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> that is <hi>Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ched in the Temple.</hi> And I think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet affirmed, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at <hi>Prayer</hi> was the <hi>onely,</hi> though ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed it was the <hi>chief,</hi> uſe of the <hi>Temple:</hi> N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ither is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re any rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on, that either the one or the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her, ſhould joſle out its <hi>Fellow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who dare affirm there is not as true &amp; real a need of <hi>Preaching</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> for Converſion t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity</hi> and Edification, as in the <hi>World</hi> for Converſion to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> of Chriſtianity? 'Tis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, the <hi>Prophets</hi> of old preached nothing more, or more frequently, to the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> then <hi>Converſion;</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame <hi>term</hi> too: and therefore, let none be ſo bold with Scripture as to call it <hi>Cant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58860:11"/>
                  <p>And let me <hi>whiſper</hi> in your Ear, that <hi>Preaching</hi> hath the <hi>preheminence</hi> of <hi>Writing,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of <hi>reading</hi> the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, both in point of <hi>time</hi> and manner of <hi>Inſtitution:</hi> which may not be thought unworthy our conſideration. We are ſure <hi>Preaching</hi> is an Ordinance ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>immediately</hi> by Chriſt himſelf, what ever <hi>Reading</hi> is; and might poſſibly, though not ſo well have delivered the mind of God the <hi>laſt two thouſand</hi> years to the World, as it did the <hi>firſt,</hi> though it had never been written. And notwithſtanding the unſpeakable advantage of the holy <hi>Scriptures, Preaching</hi> hath obtained in the <hi>univerſal Church</hi> to this day.</p>
                  <p>Who ſhall queſtion whether <hi>Preaching</hi> (whereby we <hi>addreſs</hi> to God, adoring him for his <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:58860:11"/> and <hi>truth)</hi> in the Miniſtry of the <hi>Prieſts</hi> Lips be a part of <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip?</hi> I am ſure the Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of his <hi>preſent Majeſty</hi> makes it part of <hi>divine Service.</hi> With reference to Preaching alſo we have our <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,</hi> and the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> require it at our hands.</p>
                  <p>Why ſhould our Adverſaries triumph and ſay, we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Preaching?</hi> and that we ſpeak againſt it to excuſe our <hi>idleneſs</hi> or inability? are not we beſt known by the name of <hi>Preachers?</hi> do they not by our <hi>Preaching</hi> ſee their moſt <hi>need</hi> of us? do they not hence raiſe their <hi>value</hi> and eſtimation for us? do what you can and ſpare not, to recover the honour due to the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> in <hi>other</hi> regards: But if all the reſt be loſt, I ſee no reaſon we ſhould hazard <hi>this</hi> alſo.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58860:12"/>
                  <p>It is ſaid the <hi>Preachers</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> are <hi>famous,</hi> and have long been famous through the Chriſtian World, for <hi>Preaching:</hi> Let <hi>no man</hi> take our <hi>Crown;</hi> let us not <hi>throw it away</hi> our ſelves.</p>
                  <p>2. I perceive alſo <hi>offence</hi> hath <note place="margin">Avoid So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinianiſm. and the ſuſpition of it.</note> been taken of the pretended <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional way</hi> of ſome of our <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> both in their <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Writing:</hi> Though no ſob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r man can doubt, but that it hath been of late, improved very excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, for the baffling of <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and the ſhaming of <hi>Phanaticiſm,</hi> out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the World.</p>
                  <p>But ſeeing the <hi>Law</hi> of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is twofold, <hi>viz.</hi> that of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>revelation: Phanaticiſm</hi> ſeems to be twofold alſo. When men ſo adhere to <hi>Revelation</hi> as to deſpiſe <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or ſo to glory in <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as to neglect <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> onely with this difference,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58860:12"/> the firſt do <hi>ſine Ratione,</hi> and the later <hi>cum ratione inſanire;</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the honour to run mad in the <hi>Rational</hi> way.</p>
                  <p>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thinks it is ſafeſt ſo to uſe our <hi>Reaſon</hi> about <hi>Relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on,</hi> as not to draw the ſuſpition either of <hi>Socinia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſme</hi> or <hi>Infidelity.</hi> Admit there were neither <hi>Phanatick</hi> (in ordinary ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) nor <hi>Papiſt</hi> in the World, what have we gained, if we have hazarded <hi>Chriſtianity?</hi> neither can I bear with ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and accommodated an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi> whatſoever i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s pretenſes ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, as a <hi>Jew,</hi> a <hi>Turk,</hi> or a <hi>Pagan,</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y ſubſcribe.</p>
                  <p>We glory, and that juſtly, in the great Title of <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> and we are ſet for the <hi>defenſe</hi> of it. And what is the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in ſtrictneſs of Speech, but the <hi>glad tidings</hi> of <hi>Salvation</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:58860:13"/> by <hi>Faith,</hi> in the <hi>Redemption</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Sanctification</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt:</hi> And he that ſeems to deſpiſe theſe, is not more like to a <hi>Socinian</hi> then an <hi>Infidel,</hi> but more like either then a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Is not <hi>Faith,</hi> both in the <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>profeſſion</hi> of it, a great part of the <hi>Chriſtian Religion?</hi> or is there nothing in the <hi>object</hi> of the Chriſtian Faith but what is <hi>Reaſon</hi> abſtracted from <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vela<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ion?</hi> I am not altogether ignorant of the <hi>learned</hi> attempts this way, though to no great <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</hi> I know we cannot believe, and know not <hi>why;</hi> yet we uſe to ſay, that the <hi>Arguments</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing <hi>Faith</hi> are not taken from the nature of the <hi>Object,</hi> but from the <hi>credibility</hi> or infallibility of the <hi>Author</hi> or deliverer of it. And our <hi>Faith,</hi> in the <hi>prime</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58860:13"/> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is built, not upon them as <hi>reaſonable</hi> in themſelves, but upon <hi>Teſtimony</hi> from him that cannot deceive us.</p>
                  <p>According to our <hi>Catechiſm</hi> we ſay, we <hi>believe</hi> in God the <hi>Father that made the World.</hi> Now, if Reaſon could have found out certainly that the World was <hi>made;</hi> yet that it was made by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> or by the <hi>Son of God,</hi> or that things that <hi>do</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>now appear were made of things which did not,</hi> i. e. that <hi>all things</hi> were made out of <hi>nothing;</hi> theſe things the Apoſtle, you know, referreth to <hi>Faith,</hi> as things never to have been diſcovered without <hi>ſpecial Revelation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Much leſs that thoſe other great <hi>Articles,</hi> touching the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> of Chriſt, and the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt; if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58860:14"/> you conſider them in their <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Latitude.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the Second <hi>Perſon</hi> in the <hi>Trinity</hi> ſhould aſſume the <hi>humane Nature</hi> into an <hi>Hypoſtatical union</hi> with it ſelf; that <hi>this</hi> nature ſhould be conceived by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt; born of a pure Virg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n:</hi> That there is a <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and that this <hi>is He.</hi> That he died <hi>for our ſins;</hi> that he roſe <hi>again for our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification:</hi> That he <hi>aſcended</hi> to H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n and there ſits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <hi>the right hand of God;</hi> and that thence he ſhall come <hi>again to Judge the World.</hi> All theſe are things, that <hi>Reaſon</hi> is an utter Stranger to. For <hi>great is the Myſtery of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, God manifeſted in the Fleſh,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Again, that there is a <hi>third Perſon</hi> in the <hi>Deity;</hi> that this is the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> that inſpired the <hi>Divine Writers;</hi> and <hi>confirm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:58860:14"/> the Goſpel by <hi>Miracles.</hi> That he is <hi>ſent down</hi> fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Heaven, to <hi>convince the World,</hi> to inſtruct and ſanctifie, to govern guide and comfort the Church. Theſe things we all ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dfaſtly <hi>believe</hi> as Evangelical Verities, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable by any <hi>other Light,</hi> then that of divine and ſpecial Revelation. I might add, that <hi>Repentance</hi> it ſelf, though it be a very reaſonable thing in thoſe that have offended in order to pardon, &amp;c. Yet, as it is a <hi>grace</hi> of this Spirit, and as it is a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> of the new Covenant, it is matter of <hi>Faith,</hi> and not to be diſcovered by <hi>Reaſon</hi> alone.</p>
                  <p>This is the <hi>Word of Faith</hi> that we ought to Preach, and profeſs; and thereby, give our <hi>Teſtimony that the Father ſent the Son to be the Saviour of the World, 1 Joh.</hi> 4. 14. In this, the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58860:15"/> 
                     <hi>Martyrs</hi> were all <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</hi> Search <hi>Antiquity,</hi> and you find all ancient <hi>Offices</hi> to have been compiled as it were for the ſame purpoſe. <hi>Our Church</hi> both in her <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> is a great <hi>Pillar</hi> of Chriſtianity, whereon little elſe is written but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Review our <hi>Catechiſme</hi> and <hi>Collects, Hymns</hi> and <hi>Litany,</hi> and ſeveral <hi>Creeds,</hi> as well as the <hi>Offices</hi> of the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> together with the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>end</hi> of all our <hi>Feſtivals,</hi> and particularly of the <hi>Lords day;</hi> and you cannot but be confirm'd in the acknowledgment of our <hi>great profeſſion of the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then let the World be <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del,</hi> but we that are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt, let us joy in <hi>believing;</hi> and in our places own and proſeſs the <hi>Goſpel</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58860:15"/> 
                     <hi>by Faith,</hi> which we cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend by <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us hold faſt the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and keep cloſe to the <hi>worſhip,</hi> and obſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rve the <hi>Feſtivals</hi> of our own Church as the <hi>true Sons</hi> of it, and there can be no colour for any ſuſpicion or imputation of <hi>Socinianiſme</hi> upon us.</p>
                  <p>The ſum is, notwithſtanding the <hi>private</hi> opinions of ſome men, he muſt needs be very weak that ſhall fly from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for fear of <hi>Socinianiſm:</hi> of which none can poſſibly doubt, that moreover read the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> made by the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and the reſt of our <hi>Clergy</hi> in the <hi>Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of 1640.</p>
                  <p>3. 'Tis further complain'd, <note place="margin">Nor Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Reflec. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 27.</note> that ſome of us ſpeak too much in favour <hi>of Popery;</hi> ſaying, <hi>they had rather be Papiſts then Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks,</hi> &amp;c. theſe, though I have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58860:16"/> no mind to defend, yet 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, they intend onely either thus to Droll with <hi>Phanatieks,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to ſhew an implacable <hi>averſneſs</hi> to <hi>Phanaticiſm;</hi> which, they may ſuppoſe, they can hardly do in a higher Form of Speech, then, that which prefers <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pery</hi> it ſelf before it. Though, I think the excellent Dr. is not yet anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, who hath proved <hi>Popery</hi> to be founded in the groſſeſt ſort of <hi>Phanaticiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>However, <hi>Compariſon</hi>'s, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaily, where the <hi>terms</hi> are ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite, muſt needs be offenſive and <hi>odious;</hi> yet, our Brethren ought to conſider, that ſuch ſuppoſed raſh expreſſions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect nothing upon the <hi>Church of England;</hi> which, as it owneth not ſuch extravagancy in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, ſo it ſelf is owned by <hi>them</hi> that uſe them, as the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58860:16"/> 
                     <hi>beſt Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h</hi> in the World.</p>
                  <p>But, to my <hi>Brethren</hi> I make bold to ſay, that I know no <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> they have to prefer <hi>Popery</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yond ſome ſort of <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity:</hi> I am ſure, 'tis neither <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> nor <hi>ſeaſonable.</hi> The <hi>Papiſts</hi> may know to uſe your kindneſs beyond your intention; and you find the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> are ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daliz'd at our <hi>very Church</hi> for your ſake; and <hi>puhlickly</hi> plead it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us already. And you cannot but remember the <hi>late</hi> horrid <hi>conſequences,</hi> that the groundleſs <hi>ſuſpition</hi> that our <hi>Clergy</hi> was <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> hath had upon us both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea, give me leave to ſay ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſome atleaſt of our <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comformiſts,</hi> I hope, are not worſe then <hi>Papiſts</hi> in their Principles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>civil Government;</hi> and I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58860:17"/> hope too their other principles of <hi>Religion,</hi> and their practiſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, are nearer to us then the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Neither need we look on <hi>Non-conformity,</hi> all things conſidered, as a more <hi>formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> Adverſary: In my weak opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, all that are not for <hi>Popery,</hi> have reaſon to <hi>unite</hi> againſt it.</p>
                  <p>But, whatever weakneſs <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> are guilty of in thinking otherwiſe, it is a truth, <hi>that there is no Bulwork ſo impregnable againſt Popery,</hi> as the Conſtitution of the <hi>Church of England:</hi> And none can read without ſome aſtoniſhment the incomparable <hi>Zeal</hi> of the <hi>Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> (in 1640) to ſecure our Church both from <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Socinianiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, let me conjure you not <note place="margin">Continue Loyalty:</note> to be guilty of the leaſt <hi>whiſper</hi> againſt the <hi>Government</hi> of his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58860:17"/> Sacred <hi>Majeſty;</hi> but to do your duties <hi>without murmuring.</hi> You have hitherto had the honour of being ſtyled the <hi>Loyal Clergy:</hi> 'Tis our true glory, that our <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> eſtabliſheth <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>Princes</hi> upon the beſt <hi>Principles</hi> in the World. Why ſhould it be ſaid, that the <hi>Non-conformiſts are now the Royaliſts,</hi> as an ingenuous Perſon <hi>(J. H.)</hi> intimates? Though I muſt have leave to remember <note place="margin">As it is by <hi>J. H.</hi>
                     </note> him, that herein, as well as in ſome other things, he ſeems to take too much <hi>liberty</hi> to his <hi>phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the reſt of his Brethren will ſtand to his Notion of the power of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the power of the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> touching it; I ſhould deſire to put it to no other iſſue, whether <hi>their Principle</hi> or <hi>ours,</hi> be the moſt <hi>Loyal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58860:18"/>
                  <p>He ſaith, that u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſs the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">His firſt Principles conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> of the <hi>Princes</hi> command b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>antecedently</hi> nec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſary in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Subject</hi> (it being commanded in Scripture, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the light of Nature for the common good) the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct is not <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged</hi> to ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y that command Not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing here aware, that obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce to <hi>man</hi> in things we judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>indifferent,</hi> is both commande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d in <hi>Scripture,</hi> and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <note place="margin">As he ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th him ſelf, <hi>p.</hi> 74.</note> alſo by God in the Law of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> for the <hi>common good,</hi> i. e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for the ſecurity of the publick Peace, and Gods own Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency upon the Earth.</p>
                  <p>God ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith particularly, <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves to every Ordinanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of man for the Lords ſake;</hi> that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to God. <hi>Obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> them that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ve-Rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> over you;</hi> give unto <hi>Caeſar the thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gs that are Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58860:18"/> You muſt needs be ſubject, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot onely for wealth but Conſcience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ake.</hi> Theſe are expr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſed <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lutely;</hi> but where do you find his <hi>condition,</hi> we need obey and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ubmit onely for <hi>wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th</hi> &amp; not out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <hi>Conſcie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce,</hi> if the thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anded be not otherways neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ary, or but indifferent in <hi>it ſelf?</hi> When <hi>Man</hi> commands what <hi>God</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orbids, 'tis reaſon we obey <hi>God,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hough with diſobedience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to <hi>Man;</hi> but when we may obey Man, and not diſobey God, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſt do it in obedience to God, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat is out of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The difference betwixt us is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lainly this: We ſay, the <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nce</hi> becomes obliged to ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur <hi>Prince</hi> by virtue of <hi>Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ommand,</hi> that we ſhould obey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im: You ſeem to ſay, that Conſcience becomes obliged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rom the <hi>matter</hi> or thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58860:19"/> which quite deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all obligation of <hi>Conſcienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> to obey our <hi>Prince.</hi> For you ſay when a thing is commanded by God, or we think it tends to the publick good, then onely Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is obliged to obey ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Prince:</hi> But this Obligation i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> onely from the neceſſity of the thing commanded; and becauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you approve it to be a duty <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> and conſequently in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to your own <hi>Reaſon</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Judgment, and and not at al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> or in obedience to the <hi>King;</hi> for you were in you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Log<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ck</hi> equally obliged to do it whether <hi>Man</hi> had commande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> you or not.</p>
                  <p>But in all other Caſes you need obey onely for <hi>wraths</hi> ſake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is, no further th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n you are <hi>forced:</hi> and therefore, when you
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58860:19"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re got above <hi>fear,</hi> you will not, or need not, regard <hi>Authority.</hi> This Principle will hardly pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <hi>Non-Conform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſts</hi> the onely <hi>Loyaliſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to make the matter a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le <hi>plainer;</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t us conſider what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an oblige the <hi>Conſcience</hi> but <hi>God,</hi> and the notice of his Will. Thoſe things which are <hi>indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ent</hi> in themſelves before, (as Bread and Wine) are therefore made <hi>the neceſſary Elements</hi> of the Lords Supper by Gods <hi>command,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd ought therefore to be uſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <hi>Conſcience</hi> to God. But if man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ommand any thing, there are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wo thing conſiderable; the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>atter</hi> or things commanded, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <hi>Authority</hi> or command it ſelf: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the thing commanded be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch, as God hath commanded <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>efore;</hi> we are bound <hi>in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nce</hi> to obſerve it two wayes;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58860:20"/> from the neceſſity of the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and from the <hi>Authority</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the command, which are both from God; for he that hath ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Do this</hi> hath alſo ſaid <hi>Obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> your Governours.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if the thing commande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by <hi>man</hi> were not commande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by <hi>God before,</hi> and be not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden any way by him, though the <hi>firſt</hi> way of obligation fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m the <hi>matter</hi> fails, yet the <hi>ſecon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> holds; and obligation from God to <hi>obey our G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vernours</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtill up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Conſcience, from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce of Gods will in that Caſe Beſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, as was before obſerved in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uch indiff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rent things <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> requires <hi>obedience</hi> to our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, not onely by his <hi>poſitiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Laws in <hi>Scripture,</hi> as if ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience were indifferent befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> he required it; but alſo by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Laws of <hi>Nature,</hi> for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58860:20"/> of <hi>Government</hi> and the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ublick</hi> good.</p>
                  <p>Conſider well that famous Caſe of the <hi>Recabites:</hi> They <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bſtained from Wine,</hi> in obedience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o their <hi>Fathers</hi> command after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e was <hi>dead,</hi> and all fear of his <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rath</hi> was gone: Now what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ould move or oblige them but <hi>Conſcience?</hi> Conſcience, I ſay; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot that the <hi>matter</hi> was other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe commanded by God, or was for the publick good, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <hi>honour</hi> to their <hi>dead Parent,</hi> which God comman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ore we find God <hi>approves, accepts,</hi> and <hi>rewards</hi> it. Which v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry thing proves it <hi>was ultimately</hi> and really an obedience to Gods <hi>own Will;</hi> for God <hi>approves, accepts,</hi> and <hi>rewards</hi> nothing elſé.</p>
                  <p>But the foreſaid <hi>Author</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues <note place="margin">
                        <hi>J. H.</hi> His ſecond Principle.</note> his diſcourſe to a <hi>Principle,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat ſeems to me of more <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:58860:21"/> conſequences to <hi>Government</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">P. 112, &amp;c.</note> That <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mane Powers may not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully cemmand or inforce any thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> againſt the Conſcie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ces,</hi> or perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Conſciences of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Subject,</hi> even in <hi>civil concern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> And for this inſtance he is ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turous to ſay, that a <hi>Tax</hi> may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <note place="margin">P. 118.</note> laid upon the <hi>People;</hi> yet if an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> one reſuſes to pay it, (as one o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>Fifth Monarchy,</hi> he obſerves may poſſibly, in point of <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> do) though <hi>diſtreſs may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> taken</hi> for the <hi>publick good,</hi> yet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> perſon may not lawfully be <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed</hi> for not paying it. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thus his matter runs <hi>ſmoothly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> but if we may have leave to make choice of an <hi>Inſtance,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> think he will deſire no furthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> anſwer in this particular. <hi>E. G.</hi> The <hi>Law of God</hi> is the Rule of <hi>Conſcience:</hi> This Law is <hi>Negative</hi> as well as <hi>Affirmative,</hi> and binds
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:58860:21"/> the <hi>Conſcience equally</hi> in both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. So far we are agreed. N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w admit a man of the <hi>Fifth Monarchy,</hi> or a number of ſuch men, ſhall think they are bound in <hi>Conſcience</hi> by virtue of ſome plain Text in the <hi>Revelations</hi> to <hi>deſtroy</hi> the <hi>Wicked,</hi> to ſet up the Government of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>Saints;</hi> and from that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in order to this great work, to bind the <hi>Kings of the Earth in Chains, and our Nobles in Fetters of Iron.</hi> Seriouſly ſay, what think you of this Caſe? may not the <hi>Sword</hi> of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate be made a <hi>terrour to ſuch e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Doers?</hi> may not thoſe <hi>bloody Conſciences</hi> be reſtrained by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and menaces? may not theſe bloody <hi>hands</hi> be cut off and puniſhed? may not Conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Murther</hi> be revenged? no little Artifices of mans wit, no
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58860:22"/> cunning Subterfugs of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Conſciences</hi> can poſſibly race out that indeleble Law of Nature, and the God of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; <hi>he that ſhedeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed.</hi> And if the like colour from Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence be put upon <hi>Theft, Adultery</hi> or any of the ſins againſt our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> they may eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a like Anſwer. You will ſay perhaps theſe are <hi>evil</hi> by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of <hi>Gods command,</hi> before mans Law was made; true, ſo alſo 'tis a <hi>good,</hi> which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires before the <hi>Tax</hi> be made, that we ſhould give to every one his <hi>due, Tribute</hi> to whom <hi>Tribute, Cuſtom</hi> to whom Cuſtom. And I am apt to think, that what is given to <hi>King Charles</hi> by our ſelves in <hi>Parliament,</hi> is as due to him, as what was exacted by <hi>Caeſars</hi> command was to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:58860:22"/>
                  <p>I am afr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id I ſhall trouble that Ingenious <hi>Auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I ſhould mind him, that by ſuch <hi>Principles</hi> the <hi>Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> are not lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly to carry it in point of <hi>Loyalty</hi> or tendency to <hi>Publick Good;</hi> which draw both R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ligion, and Juſtice, and <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rly</hi> it ſelf, under <hi>ſuch Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> of <hi>private Conſcience,</hi> as unh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th <hi>Government:</hi> And to ſay no worſe, leave all thoſe <hi>precious</hi> things in an uneſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed condition. But I ſpare them; for he many times ſeems to explain himſelf a great deal better then his <hi>Principle</hi> will bear him out: And ſometimes, eſpecially towards the latter end of his Book, when he had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſidered the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it, he more then ſeems to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> it, and reſolves all into the <hi>Prudence</hi> of the <hi>Governour,</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58860:23"/> no doubt finding his diſtinction of the Power of <hi>reſtraint</hi> and <hi>couſtraint</hi> would not ſerve him in all emergencies.</p>
                  <p>Let him conſider; the <hi>Law</hi> of God obligeth us to <hi>do,</hi> as well as to <hi>omit:</hi> Accordingly <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> ruled by its apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that Law, obligeth us to <hi>both:</hi> Or whether it do ſo or no, it may be <hi>perſwaded</hi> it doth, and that's all one: And though Conſcience err, yet it is to us as <hi>God;</hi> and by obeying it we obey <hi>God,</hi> and it is above all <hi>humane Authority.</hi> Therefore the Magiſtrate hath no power to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force me not to do my <hi>apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> duty; or to <hi>puniſh</hi> me if I do it, though it be to <hi>murther</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, as in the Caſe before. He abhors the <hi>conſequence,</hi> but whoſe are the <hi>premiſes?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:58860:23"/>
                  <p>After all this, and ſuppoſing ſome of us to be really guilty, either of <hi>ignorance, ſcandal, idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or <hi>imprudence</hi> in the aforeſaid particulars; I cannot be ſo fond as to believe, that this is the <hi>chief</hi> cauſe of the preſent <hi>Separation,</hi> whatever is pretended: my <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> is, becauſe it hath hitherto ſo happened (as a demonſtration to the <hi>contrary)</hi> that, where the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> themſelves acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge their <hi>Pariſh Miniſters</hi> freeſt from <hi>ſnch</hi> exceptions, (and all <hi>other)</hi> there is generally the greateſt cauſe to bewail <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Conſequently I have no great <note place="margin">No hopes; yet do your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> encouragement, without a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, to beleive, that if you ſhould <hi>reform</hi> every thing that is <hi>really</hi> amiſs in you, or that they complain of, while you are <hi>true</hi> to the <hi>duties</hi> of your places, the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58860:24"/> 
                     <hi>Separation</hi> will much abate <hi>upon</hi> it.</p>
                  <p>However, you have other ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient <hi>Motives</hi> to quicken you, &amp; other <hi>Perſons</hi> to account with: Therefore ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the fear of <hi>God,</hi> and the good of the <hi>Church</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, and remove all <hi>appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances</hi> of <hi>evil</hi> from your ſelves, and all occaſions of <hi>evil ſpeaking</hi> from the <hi>Diſſenters.</hi> And let no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing diſcourage you in your <hi>Studies</hi> and cares to <hi>amend</hi> what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s amiſs; to <hi>perſevere</hi> in well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to <hi>fulfil your Miniſtry,</hi> and to receive your <hi>Crown:</hi> And if, notwithſtanding your uttermoſt endeavours to prevent it, they will be <hi>offended,</hi> and forſake your Churches, bear it as your <hi>Croſs,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pray ſor your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note> with the <hi>patience</hi> of Chriſtians, and the <hi>courage</hi> of the <hi>men of God.</hi> And however they treat you, or the <hi>Church,</hi> ceaſe not to pity
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58860:24"/> and <hi>pray</hi> for them, as you are taught. Pray for them, though your <hi>Enemies:</hi> Though they ſlander you and <hi>perſecute</hi> you, and for nothing elſe but the truth's ſake, as they <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: That it may pleaſe thee to forgive our Enemies, Perſecutors, and Slanderers, and turn their Hearts.</hi> Pray for them as <hi>Sheep</hi> that are gone aſtray; that <hi>it may pleaſe thee to bring into the way of truth ſuch as have erred and are deceived. We beſeech thee to hear as good Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, my Brethren, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and earneſtly beſeech you to <hi>pardon</hi> my freedome with you. Onely take it by the <hi>right handle,</hi> and I know you cannot take it amiſs. Seeing 'tis ſaid I have dealt <hi>ſmartly</hi> with our <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> if I ſhould not deal <hi>plainly</hi> with you, I
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58860:25"/> ſhould neither follow my <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> nor anſwer my <hi>Reprover.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I have a word or two alſo <hi>ad populum,</hi> for our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming</hi> People, that yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>onti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in one Parochial Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:58860:25"/>
                     <head>Advice to our Conforming People.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WIll you alſo go away?</hi> you <note place="margin">Hold faſt.</note> know <hi>we have the words of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life:</hi> and whether can you go to mend your ſelves? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the danger of breaking the <hi>Union,</hi> and diſſolving the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our <hi>Pariſh Churches;</hi> and <hi>hold faſt</hi> the <hi>profeſſion of your Faith, without wavering,</hi> nor <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the aſsembling your ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Your continuing <hi>hitherto</hi> with us, declares you are <hi>ſatisfied</hi> with our Communion: And for your <hi>Pariſh Miniſters,</hi> if they are ſuch as they ſhould be, fail not to encourage them in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58860:26"/> 
                        <hi>the day of their diſtreſs,</hi> as <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> ſhould do to <hi>their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents:</hi> If they are faulty, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour in your places to <hi>reform</hi> or <hi>remove</hi> them if incorrigible, that the Church may be no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>ſcandalized</hi> by them; but be very tender of <hi>Separating</hi> from them.</p>
                     <p>Be your <hi>Miniſters</hi> never ſo obnoxious, your <hi>Separation</hi> is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>legal Remedy</hi> either for the Church or you; nor do our Laws allow it: Yea, you have not a word from the old <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> or <hi>Presbyterians</hi> to warrant your going to <hi>ſeparat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Congregations of <hi>another</hi> conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution; though indeed they did allow of going to Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour-<hi>Pariſhes,</hi> where the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter was very <hi>ignorant</hi> or <hi>wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> But if the Miniſter be pious and diligent, though of very
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58860:26"/> 
                        <hi>ordinary</hi> and mean gifts, they do by no means allow an <hi>Ordinary,</hi> and uſual with drawing from his Miniſtry, to hear thoſe that are <hi>more able.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Are the <hi>People</hi> that ſeparate of <hi>better Lives</hi> then you? the fault is not in the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> by which <hi>they</hi> were alſo generally <hi>convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> but in your <hi>ſelves: I ſpeak this to your ſhame.</hi> It is <hi>left</hi> to you, to recover the honour of of that <hi>means</hi> which <hi>they</hi> diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage by <hi>forſaking,</hi> and <hi>you</hi> by <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Yet it is ſufficiently obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the <hi>Separation</hi> it ſelf is blemiſh't with its <hi>peculiar</hi> Vices; which you ought by <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions</hi> to avoid.</p>
                     <p>Are they <hi>proud,</hi> cenſorious; <note place="margin">Vices of the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> jealous, and <hi>raſh in</hi> Judgement; be ye humble, candid, and <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tahle:</hi> Are they <hi>partial</hi> and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:58860:27"/> to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood,</hi> be ye <hi>Catholick,</hi> and as <hi>much as in you lies</hi> live <hi>peaceably</hi> with them and all men. Are they guilty of <hi>Schiſm</hi> by breach of <hi>unity?</hi> take you heed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo by breach of <hi>Charity.</hi> And by their new and ſtrange devices to <hi>deride,</hi> ſtudy how you may <hi>unite.</hi> And ſeeing they will forſake you, ſtudy you to k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ep <hi>cloſer</hi> one to another.</p>
                     <p>Yet, what is or ſeems to be <note place="margin">Their good imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate.</note> 
                        <hi>good</hi> and commendable in them, if <hi>there be any virtue,</hi> if <hi>there be any pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſe</hi> among them, <hi>think on theſe things;</hi> and diſdain not to be <hi>taught</hi> by your <hi>Adverſaries.</hi> Are they <hi>Zealous</hi> in their way? do they love and adhere to and provide one for another? are they <hi>ſtrict</hi> and temperate? Are they free from Vanity, Ribaldry, Riot, and Blaſphemy? Are they
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58860:27"/> 
                        <hi>Admirers</hi> of their <hi>Teachers.</hi> Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual and greedy obſervers of the <hi>times</hi> of their worſhip, &amp;c. Be you ſo too, and much more; and covet <hi>earneſtly the beſt gifts.</hi> Thus labouring to redeem the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Reputation</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> from the charge of a <hi>vain</hi> and debauch't <hi>Converſation,</hi> under ſo excellent a <hi>Profeſſion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58860:28"/>
                     <head>A PETITION AND ADVICE TO THE NON-CONFORMISTS.</head>
                     <p>1. TO their <hi>Preachers,</hi> if <note place="margin">Preachers.</note> they would deſign to hear me with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and charity, and <hi>meekneſs of wiſdom,</hi> and not count me an <hi>Enemy,</hi> who would onely tell them the <hi>truth in love.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Many of you are well known to me; I ſhould wrong you, not to acknowledg you to be men of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58860:28"/> 
                        <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>worth,</hi> and ſuch as are qualified to <hi>ſerve</hi> the Church in a more then ordinary man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; and I know not that I ever ſaid any thing, when <hi>warmeſt</hi> in Argument, undeſerving that Charity of <hi>J. H.</hi> concering me: <hi>who</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>upon Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, will perhaps as ſoon as any, be ready to thank God with us, if a Door ſo effectual be opened, that we may without offence, and without Schiſm, joyn our ſtrength in mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al love and concord for the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the great work of mans Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation through the Nation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Yet I have ſaid ſo much <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> you, that you will not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily believe I would <hi>flatter</hi> you: 'Tis enough, if you can bear with me, that I am not yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, but that the courſe you have taken is <hi>ſinful,</hi> and of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous <hi>conſequence;</hi> from which
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58860:29"/> very perſwaſion onely, I too<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> all that <hi>heat</hi> that ſome complai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of.</p>
                     <p>I am yet offended at your <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paration,</hi> but eſpecially that yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> gather your <hi>Aſſembl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es</hi> at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſame time with the <hi>Temple-Wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> and in ſuch <hi>Places</hi> too<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> where no exception lies againſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the <hi>Pariſh-Miniſters:</hi> Beyond all colour or pretence of Reaſon; and all <hi>Allowance</hi> even of thoſe that have hitherto Written in your <hi>defence.</hi> And methinks (ſuffer my <hi>plainneſs)</hi> if there be indeed any <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Meekneſs</hi> in you; if any love to to <hi>us;</hi> if any care to the <hi>Church;</hi> if any real deſire to avoid the Crime and the charge of <hi>Schiſm;</hi> it ſhould be difficult to perſwade you to alter your practice in that one particular.</p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58860:29"/>
                     <p>You do not think the People <note place="margin">Keep your Meetings at other t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mes.</note> would be the <hi>worſe</hi> for our Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip. You do not bid <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ce</hi> to it your ſelves; or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare againſt the <hi>Pariſh-Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of our Churches, or for a <hi>Total Separation:</hi> If any thing of this nature be ſaid of you, you are <hi>offended:</hi> Then think on't ſeriouſly, why you ſhould gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſo order your <hi>Meetings,</hi> as that your <hi>Hearers</hi> are <hi>neceſſitated</hi> to leave our Aſſemblies.</p>
                     <p>If I may not deſerve to be heard, <hi>Whom</hi> will ye hearken to in this Point? Shall we appeal <note place="margin">Follow your Friends advice.</note> to thoſe that would <hi>defend</hi> you, and Write againſt me? I am content; follow but their <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</hi> and <hi>Examples</hi> in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and you will oblige me never to trouble you more in this Matter.</p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:58860:30"/>
                     <p>Hear what the <hi>Authour of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">P. 90. 91, &amp;c.</note> 
                        <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſſention,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith: <hi>If you l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ve where the Conformable Miniſter is faithful, truly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring the Salvation of his Flock; I charge you in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ame of Chriſt, do not onely if poſſible as much as in you lieth, live in love, familiarity, peace with him; but alſo do all that you can to maintain his honour, and promote his work. For all your Non-Conformity, you are no better then</hi> he, if you be not more <hi>charitable</hi> then he. <hi>If you ſet your ſelves in a dividing way, ſecretly to rejoyce at his diſparagement, and to draw as many from him as you can, you are but deſtroyers of the Church of God. Call your ſelves what you will, I will call you deſtroyers if you are dividers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Yea, much that elſe would be your duty, muſt be omitted to avoid Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion. The work of God, the good of Souls, the defenſe of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58860:30"/> Religion againſt Papiſts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire your utmoſt conjured ſtrength: And you are Betrayers of all theſe, if you are Dividers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore go as often as you can to his Congregation; and hold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion perſonally with him, and lead the People with you. Do not ſay now we have an opportunity to do better, it is unlawful to joyn with them that do worſe: For though it be not lawful to neglect your own duty and opportunity, it is lawful for you by deed as well as word to ſhew your Chriſtian Concord and Communion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therefore in Pariſhes where all may well hear the Pariſh Miniſter, I would not have you, without neceſſity Preach at the ſame hour as he doth, but at ſome middle time, that you may not ſeem to vie with him for Auditors, nor to draw the People from him: But let them go with you to hear him, and after come and hear you, or before.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:58860:31"/>
                     <p>And that he likes not this <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of Churches</hi> very well, whatever he had ſaid in the <hi>defenſe,</hi> by the <hi>Petition</hi> he would have <hi>us</hi> make for them: <hi>That if poſſible</hi> (upon the terms he had laid down) <hi>they might be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the eſtabliſhed Miniſtry; if not, yet tolerated as Lecturers under us in ſuch Churches where the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters deſire</hi> them. And he hath my conſent, that either of theſe were <hi>rather</hi> to be admitted, though it be with the <hi>loſs</hi> of part of our <hi>profits,</hi> then to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard <hi>all,</hi> as I fear you do, by the preſent <hi>ſeparation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>One thing, I humbly renew for your moſt ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; whether it be not adviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to inſtruct your <hi>Hearers,</hi> in the lawfulneſs and <hi>conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of their communicating <hi>with us,</hi> at leaſt ſometimes;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58860:31"/> and perſwading them there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to both by your <hi>teachi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>g</hi> and <hi>example;</hi> leſt by the conſtant <hi>oppoſite practice,</hi> their hearts be ſo <hi>alienated</hi> from the <hi>Temple wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> that when you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to it, you ſhall find it beyond your power.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:58860:32"/>
                     <head>To the Non-Conforming People</head>
                     <p>FOr you that are our <hi>People,</hi> who are neither gone away <hi>already,</hi> or are under temptation to <hi>leave us,</hi> I have very little encouragement to trouble you with my advice; though I ſhall not ſay of <hi>you,</hi> as the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> lately quoted doth of the <note place="margin">P. 118.</note> 
                        <hi>Conformiſts</hi> in his <hi>humble Petition</hi> to them, <hi>that Satan hath got ſo great advantage, that the wiſeſt man living is uncapable of ſpeaking rightly to them without offence.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>However ſuffer, though it be a kind of <hi>penance</hi> to you, yet ſuffer a word or two of <hi>Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> which I ſhall commend
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:58860:32"/> with better <hi>Authority</hi> to you, then mine own.</p>
                     <p>1. Suffer the Arguments both <note place="margin">Conform as far as you can.</note> from <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>unity</hi> and <hi>charity,</hi> to prevail with you, to conform as <hi>far as you can.</hi> And in what you cannot, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and if that cannot be had, uſe any <hi>allowed</hi> means for the gratifying your ſelves in <hi>ſuch things</hi> wherein you <hi>cannot</hi> conform; but do not <hi>ſeparate more then you muſt needs;</hi> Is not this <hi>reaſonable</hi> and <hi>proper</hi> advice? ask Mr. <hi>Baxier?</hi> ask the <hi>Author</hi> of the Anſwer to my Book? ask the old <hi>Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts;</hi> yea I appeal to your <hi>own Breaſts,</hi> if you would but ſuffer your ſelves ſeriouſly and impartially to conſider it: For ſurely <hi>Diviſion</hi> is not to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen <hi>for it ſelf;</hi> and there can be no reaſon for the uſe of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58860:33"/> 
                        <hi>Phyſick</hi> of Separation, and rending and tearing the <hi>body</hi> of the Church, beyond <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There are three Queſtions or <hi>Caſes</hi> of Conſcience, that would be <hi>throughly</hi> canvas'd and reſolv'd before yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Separate.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. Whether we may <hi>ordinarily leave our own Pariſh Miniſters</hi> to <hi>hear others?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Whether ſuch as could and did communicate with the Pariſh Churches before the liberty, can have any tolerable reaſon to ſeparate now.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether ſuch as ſay they cannot in Conſcience joine with us in all things, have any ground to leave us in thoſe Parts of worſhip they can.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The firſt is anſwered by the <hi>Old Non-Conformiſts;</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by the grave Mr. <hi>Hilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham,</hi> in theſe words:</p>
                     <q>
                        <pb n="63" facs="tcp:58860:33"/>
                        <p>If thy <hi>Paſtor,</hi> ſaith he, be <hi>approved</hi> of by the Church <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable</hi> in his <hi>place, unblameable</hi> in his life; though of <hi>inferiour Parts,</hi> take heed thou leave him not.</p>
                        <p>1. He may be a true <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> though <hi>inferiour</hi> to many others, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 15. Which Argument the Apoſtle uſeth to perſwade <hi>all</hi> members to <hi>unity,</hi> Eph. 4. 7.</p>
                        <p>You are bound to love and <hi>reverence</hi> him, and thank God for him. <hi>1 Cor. 6. 10. 1 Theſ. 5. 13. Rom. 10. 15. Luke 10. 16.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>3. Doubtleſs thou maiſt <hi>profit</hi> by him, if the fault be not <hi>in thy ſelf,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 7. &amp; 14. 31.</p>
                        <p>4. Our <hi>profit</hi> depends not on Miniſters <hi>gifts,</hi> but on Gods <hi>bleſſing,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:58860:34"/>
                        <p>5. None may uſually and <hi>ordinarily</hi> leave his own <hi>Paſtour,</hi> (ſo qualified as before) for: 1. As it is Gods own <hi>Ordinance,</hi> that every own <hi>Paſtour</hi> ſhould have his own <hi>Flock</hi> to attend, and take heed unto, <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 23. So it is Gods <hi>Ordinance,</hi> that every one of Gods People ſhould have a <hi>Paſtor</hi> of his own to attend upon, <hi>1 Pet. 5. 3.</hi> Now he cannot be ſaid to depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Paſtour's</hi> Miniſtry, that doth <hi>ordinarily</hi> and uſually leave it, and go to another. He onely maketh a <hi>right</hi> uſe of the <hi>benefit</hi> of <hi>hearing</hi> ſuch as have more <hi>excellent</hi> gifts then his own <hi>Paſtour,</hi> as leaneth thereby to his own <hi>Paſtour</hi> the better, and to <hi>profit more</hi> by him.</p>
                        <p>6. If thou leaveſt thine own <hi>Paſtour</hi> onely with a deſire to <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie</hi>
                           <pb n="65" facs="tcp:58860:34"/> thy ſelf. 1. Do it with <hi>his conſent</hi> and leave. 2. Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thou oweſt a <hi>duty</hi> to him as to thy <hi>Superiour</hi> in the things that belong to thy <hi>Soul,</hi> 1. Theſ. 5. 11. 3. Thou art bound to ſeek his <hi>comfort,</hi> and to give him all good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, that he may do his work with <hi>joy</hi> and cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Heb. 13. 17. Hilderſham</hi> upon the 4<hi>th.</hi> of <hi>John.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </q>
                     <p>2. The Second Caſe is touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>ſuch of you as could and did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ommunicate with us in our Pariſh worſhip, before the liberty granted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y the late Declaration:</hi> And is, whether they can have any <hi>tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>le Reaſon</hi> (except their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be ſince changed) to <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ate now.</hi> That they cannot, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ope I have made to appear ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ciently in other parts; but if <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y Reaſons</hi> may not be thought
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58860:35"/> worthy your Conſideration; yet, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> thinks 'tis not in conſiderable, that there are but <hi>two</hi> Perſons that have ſet themſelves to <hi>anſwer</hi> me; and they have both of them yielded <hi>in this point.</hi> Though they ſeem to be a little <hi>too</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptious in leſſer matters.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Author</hi> of the Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sacrilegious deſertion of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſtry rebuked,</hi> &amp;c. deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf in the Caſe fully to our purpoſe in theſe words.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>As far as I can promiſe <note place="margin">P. 76.</note> ſaith he, we will judge of you no worſe then <hi>we have done,</hi> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> deny any Communion with you which we <hi>have</hi> uſed, and <hi>can</hi> uſe, without neglecting ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> own work. As I conſtantl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Joyn in my <hi>Pariſh Church</hi> in <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi> and <hi>Sac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>aments,</hi> ſo I hop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to do <hi>while I live,</hi> (if I live un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as honeſt a Miniſter) at du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> times.</q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:58860:35"/>
                     <p>The Author of the <hi>ſhort Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections</hi> upon <hi>Toleration not to be</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">P. 37.</note> 
                        <hi>abuſed,</hi> is my other <hi>publick Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary;</hi> let us hear him alſo. <q>Who are they, ſaith he, who ſeparate from them where they <hi>can have Communion</hi> with them, I do not know. (I wiſh we could ſay ſo too.) Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians I believe will not ſcruple to hear all Miniſters amongſt them to Preach (as they have occaſion) nor poſſibly ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hear them read. COMMON PRAYER, but will be ready to go with him <hi>as far as they can.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus alſo you have <hi>their</hi> opinion as to the laſt Caſe, viz. <hi>Whether ſuch as ſay they cannot in Conſcience joyn with us in all things, have any ground to leave us in thoſe parts of worſhip wherein they can?</hi> You have heard both
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58860:36"/> theſe <hi>Authors,</hi> when they pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſet themſelves to ſpeak to theſe very points, to intimate their Confeſſion for the <hi>Negative.</hi> Upon this very ground <hi>Ames</hi> ſeems to affirm, there may be no <hi>total Separation</hi> from a true Church, but onely <hi>partial, quatenus Communio non poteſt abſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> peccato exerceri,</hi> ſo far as we may not communicate without ſin.</p>
                     <p>What man can think it reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that ſuch as live within the <hi>bounds</hi> of any true particular <hi>Church,</hi> ſhould for <hi>ſome offences</hi> renounce <hi>all Communion</hi> with it? or, as I ſaid at firſt, divide and <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate more then needs?</hi> When once you can weigh the evil of <hi>diviſion,</hi> and value <hi>Peace</hi> in the Church, and <hi>union</hi> amongſt Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren truly as you ought; you will be then of the ſame mind with with us. O let no prejudice or
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58860:36"/> 
                        <hi>partial</hi> reſpect of <hi>things</hi> or <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> any longer captivate your minds in <hi>Errour,</hi> leading to a <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> ſo dangerous in its <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> as I have ſhewn; and ſo unreaſonable in its <hi>Principles,</hi> as your ſtouteſt <hi>Friends,</hi> in the <hi>Field</hi> of controverſie would not dare to defend. Yea, whoſe very <hi>Profeſſions</hi> and perſonal <hi>Practices</hi> are for the contrary, and would teach you better.</p>
                     <p>My <hi>firſt</hi> Anſwerer hath many other very good <hi>Directions</hi> both to <hi>you</hi> and your <hi>Teachers,</hi> for which I thank him; and which I earneſtly deſire you to conſider and <hi>follow.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:58860:37"/>
                     <head>Remarques upon the late Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on Toleration not to be abuſed.</head>
                     <p>THeſe <hi>ſhore Reflections</hi> might have been much <hi>ſhorter,</hi> and none of the Authors <hi>Reaſon</hi> been loſt: <hi>Some</hi> of them might have been ſpared, for that they <hi>reflect</hi> upon the <hi>Author</hi> himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as <hi>theſe: Bleſsed God! when will the luſt of implacable men be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied upon their Brethren!</hi> p. 5. <hi>the Author ſeems to be incredibly ſerious,</hi> p. 6. <hi>Doth it not ſeem ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to you?</hi> p. 22. <hi>'Tis both ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious and nonſenſical imputation.</hi> p. 22. <hi>They may it ſeems toler atc any thing, but his Majeſty may not,</hi>
                        <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58860:37"/> p. 25. <hi>as to the fear of Popery, I wiſh he and his Friends were in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,</hi> p. 27. <hi>'Tis well known moſt of the Conformiſts are</hi> Arminians, p. 28. <hi>If he had favour'd me with his Notion of a true particular Church,</hi> &amp;c. but <hi>this was not for Intereſt,</hi> p. 29.</p>
                     <p>Theſe, and ſuch kind of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections,</hi> ſeem not to be worthy of a <hi>pure light;</hi> that ſo lately came out of great <hi>darkneſs</hi> and <hi>tribulation;</hi> as he every where complains: But <hi>this kind</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections I have no mind to <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I have indeed made <hi>reply</hi> to <hi>all</hi> the other parts of his Book: But, upon <hi>Second</hi> thoughts have yet reſolved to <hi>publiſh</hi> onely ſo much of it, as concerns the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, ſo far as it is <hi>New;</hi> and not ſo fully conſidered as, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, might be deſired, in my
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58860:38"/> 
                        <hi>Reply</hi> to my other <hi>Anſwerer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The very <hi>Queſtion</hi> almoſt in <note place="margin">Tit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e page.</note> 'his own words is this: <hi>Whether it be not a ſinful Separation, and contrary to the Principles of the late Presbyterians, to gather them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into Congregations diſtinct and ſeparate from the parochial Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, under preſent Circ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>mſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> Thus I affi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m, and he deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Sum</hi> of that which he offereth againſt it, is reduceable to theſe <hi>two Propoſit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ons:</hi> 1. We hold the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a <hi>true Church,</hi> and yet <hi>Separate</hi> from it. 2. Our <hi>Parochial</hi> are not <hi>true</hi> Churches; or at leaſt they are ſo <hi>faulty,</hi> as they may lawfully be <hi>ſeparated</hi> from.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe is much inſiſted on by my <hi>other</hi> Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to whom I have <hi>anſwered</hi> in another place: we find it <hi>twice,</hi>
                        <pb n="73" facs="tcp:58860:38"/> at leaſt in theſe <hi>Reflections,</hi> p. 17. by the ſame Weapon, ſaith he, <hi>by which our Brerhren aefend their Separation from</hi> Rome, <hi>we defend our Seceſſion in ſome Ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ances from them.</hi> But how you ſhall defend your Seceſſion <hi>in all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> would alſo be conſidered. But more briskly to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>p.</hi> 23. he queries thus; <hi>Have not our Brethren Separated from the Church of</hi> Rome; <hi>yet many of them do own the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>as a true Church? When they have reconciled themſelves to to theſe aſſertions of their own, they will be able to ſee what anſwer we may give them alſo. If they may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from a Church which they own as true, then ſurely we may do ſo too.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But hereunto I anſwer.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. When I affirmed that it was <hi>unlawful to gather a Church out of a</hi>
                        <pb n="74" facs="tcp:58860:39"/> 
                        <hi>true Church</hi> (which was the ground of his <hi>Reflection,)</hi> I did <hi>perſonate</hi> and ſpake the <hi>propoſitior</hi> of the <hi>late Presbyterians.</hi> And you do not ſay, the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans hold the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a <hi>true</hi> Church: So that as to them, the Argument may be ſtill valid enough. And thoſe of us, that you ſay hold the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a true Church, may have, and indeed have, <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arguments</hi> to condemn your Separation.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. You know that was a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Argument of the <hi>late Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> againſt the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents;</hi> and I uſed it as <hi>theirs:</hi> And if it be <hi>inconſequent,</hi> charge <hi>them</hi> with bad Logick, and <hi>ſay they</hi> were miſtaken, not I.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. 'Tis moſt certain, this is no good Logick with the <hi>old Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians:</hi> We may ſeparate from the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58860:39"/> Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> therefore from the <hi>Church of England.</hi> And when they urge their Adverſaries with the <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> of gathering Churches out of true Churches, they ſuppoſed they ſpake to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that underſtood what <hi>true Churches</hi> they meant, <hi>viz.</hi> Our <hi>Parochial</hi> Congregations. And that out of <hi>ſuch</hi> true Churches as ours are, where we have <hi>the Word and Sacraments truly</hi> diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and we may communicate without ſin, it is not lawful to ſeparate and gather Churches.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. It is not enongh for you to ſay our Communion is ſo <hi>corrupt,</hi> as you cannot communicate in it; we <hi>prove</hi> that the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Roman Church</hi> is ſuch. Upon this ground the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> the <hi>Quaker,</hi> the vileſt Separatiſt and Heretick is armed; and may as well ſay, you ſeparate from <hi>Rome,</hi> that you take to be a true
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58860:40"/> Church; therefore we may ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from <hi>you,</hi> whether ye be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o or not.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. For the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> many of them do indeed hold the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>verè</hi> a Church of Chriſt; yet generally they ſay ſhe is not <hi>vera Eccleſia:</hi> ſhe is truly a Church as to the <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> but not <hi>morally a true Church,</hi> having neither the <hi>Word truly Preached, nor the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred in it;</hi> which <hi>Calvin</hi> makes Eſſential to a <hi>true Church.</hi> I dare undertake to make it evident, when he ſhall <hi>vouchſafe to name thoſe principal Fathers,</hi> whom now he is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth <hi>unwilling</hi> to name; (for what Reaſon I know not) I dare undertake, I ſay, to make it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that they meant no other <hi>thing,</hi> though they may take
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:58860:40"/> the <hi>Liberty</hi> of their own <hi>words.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. The <hi>ſum</hi> is; the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> hold the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a <hi>falſe</hi> Church; and ſay, you may not gather a Church out of a <hi>true</hi> Church. The <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal</hi> Divines ſay, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>truely</hi> a Church, but not <hi>true</hi> as a Church ſhould be, but <hi>falſe</hi> and corrupt both in her <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Worſhip;</hi> ſo as none can lawfully <hi>joyn</hi> with her: And yet the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> is both <hi>truly</hi> a Church and a a <hi>true</hi> Church; where the <hi>Word of God is truly taught, whoſe Doctrine the very Non-Conformiſts approve of;</hi> &amp; in whoſe worſhip, many of them ſay, we may joyn <hi>without ſin;</hi> where the <hi>Sacraments</hi> are alſo <hi>rightly</hi> adminiſtred: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, without all further contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie they may hold that it is <hi>lawful</hi> to <hi>ſeparate</hi> from the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58860:41"/> Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but <hi>ſinful</hi> to ſeparate from the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and yet not be able to ſee what <hi>Anſwer</hi> you may give them.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Beſides, <hi>laſtly,</hi> you may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily know, that our eminent <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> ſay; that, if we are <hi>in Schiſm</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves were guilty of it in <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> yea, that we did not, do not <hi>ſeparate</hi> from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for we <hi>really</hi> were never of that Church: We never did <hi>owe</hi> any <hi>Communion</hi> to to that Church: That, under the encouragement of <hi>own Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and by the authority thereof, we onely <hi>reformed our</hi> ſelves, without ſeparating from <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other Church. And if ſo, as in truth it is, much good may your <hi>Conſequence</hi> do you.</p>
                     <p n="8">
                        <pb n="79" facs="tcp:58860:41"/>8. But he alſo intimates a <hi>Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> upon <hi>our Churches:</hi> He doth not indeed ſpeak <hi>out;</hi> but he ſpeaks as if our <hi>Parochial Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies,</hi> were either no <hi>true Churches,</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> as we may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>Separate</hi> from. Hear him <hi>p.</hi> 15. where he <hi>firſt co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cedes fairly; We do believe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that from a Church, a number of Chriſtians that have conſented to a Paſtor that is able and faithful, and regularly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſters the Ordinances of Chriſt, ſo as a People may communicate without ſin; and preſſing forward towards perfection in order, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians may not ſeparate without ſin.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And this is <hi>that</hi> indeed, ſaith he, <hi>which ſome Presbyterians re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon our Brethren of the Congregational way for: And theſe were thoſe Parochial Churches, which they contended for as true Churches.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:58860:42"/>
                     <p>And now the <hi>bottom</hi> is out, and his <hi>Fallicy</hi> is apparent in his <hi>foiſting</hi> (I would uſe an <hi>eaſier</hi> word if I could) his foiſting in <hi>now</hi> and ſtrange <hi>matter</hi> into the <hi>nature</hi> of a <hi>true Church;</hi> and then fathering it upon the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> when 'tis purely <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, Browniſtical,</hi> or his <hi>own.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For, if there be any <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> in what he hath ſaid, 'tis this: A Church where the <hi>Paſtor</hi> is duly qualified, and the People <hi>conſent</hi> to him; and both <hi>preſs forward</hi> towards perfection in <hi>order;</hi> you may not <hi>ſeparate</hi> from: But if the <hi>Paſtor</hi> be not in all points well qualified, or if the People do not <hi>approve</hi> of him, or if they do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> preſs forward towards <hi>perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in <hi>order,</hi> one may <hi>ſeparat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> from <hi>ſuch</hi> a Church, and the <hi>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Presbyterians</hi> ſaid nothing to the contrary.</p>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:58860:42"/>
                     <p>But, ſuppoſe the <hi>Paſtor</hi> be <hi>faulty</hi> in ſome particulars of his <hi>life,</hi> if he regularly adminiſters in his <hi>Office;</hi> or ſuppoſe, he be a <hi>good man,</hi> and a diligent <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter,</hi> and be ſet over a People by the <hi>Laws</hi> of our own Church, but the <hi>People</hi> do not <hi>like</hi> him; will you ſay, this is no <hi>true Church</hi> for <hi>theſe Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons?</hi> If you are a <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> you dare not. May one <hi>ſeparate</hi> from ſuch a Church for theſe Reaſons? or for theſe Reaſons may you betake your ſelf to a Church of <hi>another Conſtitution?</hi> was ever <hi>this</hi> the <hi>opinion</hi> of the <hi>Old Non-Conformiſts</hi> or <hi>late Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians?</hi> Say it not for ſhame.</p>
                     <p>But the weight is behind, in the laſt <hi>condition: Preſſing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward towards Perfection in order. Theſe were the Parochial Churches, where this excellency was found;</hi>
                        <pb n="82" facs="tcp:58860:43"/> 
                        <hi>which the late Presbyterians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ended for as true Churches.</hi> Thus he would draw his <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Brethren to own that which is contrary to their expreſs ſenſe and words; for they did <hi>ex pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſo</hi> diſpute, that <hi>order</hi> and diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline was not eſſential to a true Church; and onely for the want of it none might ſeparate.</p>
                     <p>In earneſt: Suppoſe a Church thinks <hi>her Order,</hi> as to the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> is as perfect as ſhe can, or need to have it: And ſhe deſires that the <hi>Execution</hi> were better, but cannot have it ſo. Yea, ſuppoſe a Church <hi>too careleſs</hi> in this matter, whether it be well or no; will you, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Presbyterian</hi> ſay, it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no <hi>true Church,</hi> or we may therefore ſeparate from it? Was not <hi>this</hi> the Caſe of the Church of <hi>Corinth?</hi> Doth the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>
                        <pb n="83" facs="tcp:58860:43"/> adviſe or allow any <hi>Separation</hi> in this caſe? Though their <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> alſo was more corrupt then <hi>Arminianiſm</hi> that ſo much offends you, and their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> debauched even with <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance</hi> and Luxury.</p>
                     <p>Beſides, whatever unjuſt and unconſcionable clamours we labour under, we are ready to maintain, that our <hi>Miniſters, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally,</hi> are of holy and unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Lives;</hi> and do faithfully, and regularly adminiſter both the <hi>Word and Sacraments;</hi> and that our <hi>People generally</hi> do, or very lately did, ſubmit to their <hi>Parochial Miniſters,</hi> and really own them as <hi>their Guides,</hi> by their attendance upon the worſhip of God in our <hi>Temples;</hi> and thoſe <hi>few</hi> that did not, I hope I have ſufficiently proved that <hi>they ought</hi> to have done it.</p>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:58860:44"/>
                     <p>And now I ſhall venture to <hi>appeal</hi> to the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecter</hi> himſelf, whether ſo <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> and <hi>total</hi> a defection and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion from a <hi>true Church</hi> (as he ſeemeth to acknowledge <hi>ſome</hi> of ours to be; and if any, ſure they are ſuch as they <hi>ſeparate from)</hi> would have been judged <hi>other</hi> then <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> by the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> themſelves, or by the <hi>Fathers,</hi> or by the <hi>reformed Churches</hi> beyond Sea, or by our own ancient <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> if no other Reaſon could be alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it, but what he hath here urged? As for the <hi>late Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> indeed it is the very <hi>queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> what <hi>they</hi> thought of this point; and whether it be lawful, in <hi>their Judgment</hi> for ſuch <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> as he hath brought us, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate, and to gather our People into <hi>new Churches,</hi> will better ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58860:44"/> from their <hi>own</hi> words, for they can yet ſpeak <hi>for themſelves,</hi> and you will find they do it fully in the following <hi>Dialogue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>What the <hi>Reflection</hi> means by <note place="margin">P. 14.</note> putting <hi>[A Subjection in all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the Goſpel to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt]</hi> into the <hi>definition</hi> of the Church, I cannot certainly divine; but if it ſignifie any thing more then the <hi>received De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitions</hi> of a true Church, it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies <hi>nothing</hi> but an <hi>Engine</hi> of <hi>Diviſions.</hi> The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will have it in, to ſerve his <hi>Ruling Elder:</hi> The <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi> to keep out all <hi>Forein Juriſdiction,</hi> and keep himſelf exempt from all power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the bounds of a <hi>particular Church:</hi> The <hi>Anabaptiſt,</hi> for the <hi>neceſſity of Baptizing,</hi> as <hi>neceſſary</hi> to a <hi>true Church.</hi> And thus it becomes an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58860:45"/> for the <hi>mutual damning</hi> one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
                     <p>Whereas, if the difinition of <hi>Calvin</hi> and reformed Divines keep its authority <hi>(viz.</hi> that <hi>where the Word of God is truly preach'd, and the Sacraments right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtred, there is a true Church)</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath room enough for his <hi>large Charity,</hi> to think they are <hi>all true</hi> Churches, though <hi>Schiſmatical:</hi> That is, though they are made up of <hi>Sheep gone aſtray</hi> from their <hi>proper Folds;</hi> to which they yet <hi>owe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> and ought to return.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58860:45"/>
                  <p>A Dialogue BETWIXT THE INDEPENDENT AND PRESBYTERIAN About gathering of CHURCHES;</p>
                  <p>Taken out of a Book called, the <hi>Grand Debate,</hi> and <hi>Papers</hi> therein Printed, as they were given in to the <hi>Committy</hi> of Lords and Commons, and Aſſembly of Divines, with the Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> for Acommodation 1644. Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in 1648.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>James Collins,</hi> at the Kings Arms in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1673.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58860:46"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58860:46"/>
                  <head>TO THE Reader.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PErhaps thou mayeſt cenſure me too</hi> ſevere <hi>with my</hi> Anſwerers, <hi>in exppoſing this</hi> old difference <hi>to a</hi> publick <hi>review: but why then did they give me ſo great an</hi> advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, <hi>and provoke me to take it in my own defenſe? Why did they</hi> Scandalize <hi>the World, and many of their own</hi> Friends <hi>too, who are yet</hi> living Witneſſes <hi>of that ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious a conteſt? by mincing the matter &amp; ſeeming ſhy to acknowledge that the</hi> then Presbyterians <hi>were againſt gathering</hi> new <hi>Churches out of the</hi> Parochial? <hi>To ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their opinion of</hi> Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>For what Toleration, as to</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58860:47"/> our purpoſe, <hi>could they, that were Presbyterians, be thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> indulge, who ſo ſtifly refuſed to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it to their</hi> Independent <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, particularly in the very point of</hi> gathering Churches.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In this following</hi> Dialogue <hi>you have no feigned</hi> diſguiſe <hi>on either ſide; but both ſpeaking</hi> over again <hi>their own</hi> Senſe, <hi>and</hi> Reaſon, <hi>and</hi> words <hi>throughout, almoſt</hi> verba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim. <hi>As they were given in by</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>to the</hi> Committee <hi>of the long</hi> Parliament, <hi>as appears in the ſecond part of the</hi> grand Debate, <hi>publiſhed by Perſons intruſted by both</hi> Parties.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By way of</hi> Introduction: <hi>You need not be remembred that the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>were earneſt for an</hi> eſtabliſhment <hi>with</hi> Uniformity, <hi>and did declare that the Members of</hi> particular <hi>Congregations do</hi> cohabit <hi>and live together,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:58860:47"/> 
                     <hi>within certain</hi> bounds <hi>and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of a Pariſh,</hi> p. 6. n. 9. <hi>The</hi> Independents, <hi>not well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, moved for an</hi> Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, <hi>and the Dialague may be ſuppoſed to begin thus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="dialogue">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:58860:48"/>
                  <head>A DIALOGUE Betwixt the INDEPENDENT AND PRESBYTERIAN, Taken out of Papers given to the Committee of Lords and Commons, and Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines, with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> for Accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, 1644. Printed, 1648.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>WE are not againſt your <hi>Rule,</hi> and the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you deſire; onely we cannot in <hi>Conſcionce</hi> be ſo confined: And therefore we deſire <hi>liberty</hi> to worſhip God in our own way <hi>by our ſelves.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <pb n="93" facs="tcp:58860:48"/>Presh.</speaker>
                     <p>We are not altogether againſt an <hi>Indulgence;</hi> but we would have none allowed the <hi>benefit</hi> of it, but ſuch as agree with us as to the ſubſtance of their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>Therefore you cannot deny it to <hi>us,</hi> who <hi>thus</hi> agree with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presh.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. But your deſire plainly holds out a <hi>total ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> As if our Churches were not to be communicated with <hi>in any thing</hi> which ſhould argue <hi>Church-Communion:</hi> and more could not be ſaid or done againſt <hi>falſe Churches.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. It alſo plainly holds out the lawfulneſs of <hi>gathering Churches</hi> out of true Churches; yea (they add, by way of aggravation the cauſe of our <hi>Reflecters</hi> miſtake) ſuch <hi>true Churches</hi> as endeavour further to <hi>reform:</hi> Whereof we
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58860:49"/> are aſſured, there is not the leaſt hint of an <hi>Example</hi> in the <hi>Word</hi> of God.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. This <hi>liberty</hi> would pull down what the <hi>Parliament</hi> would ſet up, and would give you a <hi>greater</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge then we enjoy, who are under the Rule <hi>of eſtabliſhment.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. This would give counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to a <hi>perpetual Schiſm</hi> and Diviſion in the Church; ſtill drawing away from the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es under the <hi>Rule,</hi> &amp;c. and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce all manner of confuſion in <hi>Families,</hi> where the Members are of ſeveral Churches.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>What <hi>liberty</hi> then are you contented to allow us, that differ from you almoſt in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>matters of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>None may be allowed, upon differences onely in <hi>matter of Government,</hi> to withdraw Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58860:49"/> from us in things wherein they declare an <hi>agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>—There may be no ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence granted to any, as may conſtitute them in <hi>diſtinct Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,</hi> as <hi>to thoſe parts of</hi> worſhip where they can <hi>joyn</hi> in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us. Onely ſome expedient may be found to <hi>bear</hi> with them in the particulars wherein they <hi>cannot agree</hi> with us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>What expedient?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>Such as through <hi>ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> or error of <hi>Conſcience</hi> cannot joyn to parta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> ſhall repair to the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> and Elders for <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> in their <hi>Scruples,</hi> which if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive, they ſhall not be compelled to <hi>communicate.</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that in all other parts of worſhip they joyn with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, in which they live,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58860:50"/> and be under the Government of that Congregation. So far you have in <hi>p.</hi> 18, 19, 20, &amp;c.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>If this be <hi>all,</hi> we muſt be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ain with you; We can't joyn with you <hi>without ſin:</hi> We would not li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ve <hi>without Ordinances:</hi> And for the enjoyment of them, for for our <hi>ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>cation,</hi> we would joyn in <hi>another</hi> Congregation.</p>
                     <p>Yet ſo as not <hi>condemning</hi> thoſe Churches we joyn not with, as falſe; but ſtill preſerving all <hi>Chriſtian Communion</hi> with the <hi>Saints</hi> of the ſame body of the <hi>Church Catholick,</hi> and joyn with them in all duties of worſhip, that belong to particular Churches, <hi>ſo far as we are able:</hi> If this be called <hi>Schiſme,</hi> or the countenance of Schiſm, it is more than we have yet learned, <hi>p.</hi> 36.</p>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:58860:50"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Is not this a very fair Plea? It was once Independency. And the Presbyterians then anſwer'd to it in every particular.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>We cannot <hi>without ſin</hi> to us, enjoy all the Ordinances of Chriſt, and partake of all duties of worſhip <hi>as Members</hi> of that Congregation <hi>where our dwelling is:</hi> And what would you have us do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>If you cannot in <hi>all,</hi> yet partake in <hi>as many</hi> duties and ordinances as you can: And let the <hi>Indulgence</hi> onely <hi>ſupply</hi> that, wherein you <hi>cannot;</hi> and not exempt you univerſally in that wherein you <hi>can.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But we deſire you would ſpeak freely and candidly: Can you enjoy <hi>any one</hi> Ordinance in our Congregation <hi>as Members?</hi> We ſhould be glad to hear from you, that you can be <hi>Members</hi> of that
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58860:51"/> Congregation where <hi>your dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is</hi> p. 70.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>But you know we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live <hi>without Ordinances</hi> for our edification: Therefore for our ſpiritual good, we may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully joyn in <hi>another Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. This will not follow upon your own <hi>Conceſſion:</hi> For you conſeſs you can <hi>occaſionally</hi> joyn with us without ſin; and why not <hi>conſtantly?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. Your Conſcience may <hi>erre:</hi> And the Church is no way bound to <hi>indulge</hi> a liberty then, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the evident <hi>diſturbance</hi> of her own peace.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Whatever <hi>indulgence</hi> is granted, let this be the <hi>boundary</hi> of it, which is given by our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren themſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> that ſuch as give no <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of their <hi>Godlineſs</hi> and <hi>Peaceableneſs;</hi> ſuch as
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58860:51"/> have not uſed <hi>all means</hi> in faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to know the mind of Chriſt; ſuch as do condemn thoſe Churches which they joyn not with, <hi>as falſe;</hi> as do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve all <hi>Chriſtian Communion</hi> with the Saints; nor joyn with them in all duties of worſhip ſo far as they are able, ſhall not have the benefit of this indulgence.</p>
                     <p>And to the end that theſe words [ſo far as they are able] may not ſtand for a meer <hi>Cypher,</hi> and ſignifie nothing; let each man particularly declare in what ordinances he is <hi>able</hi> to joyn: that ſo all total Separation may be prevented, <hi>p. 70.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>Though we ſhall not joyn with, we will not <hi>condemn</hi> your Churches as <hi>falſe:</hi> And this no <hi>rigid Separation,</hi> p. 71.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>The <hi>condemning</hi> our <hi>Churches as falſe,</hi> doth <hi>little exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate</hi>
                        <pb n="100" facs="tcp:58860:52"/> the Separation: For di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the <hi>Browniſts</hi> who have <hi>totally</hi> ſeparated in former times, have not condemned theſe Churches as falſe.</p>
                     <p>Though you do not pronounce an <hi>affirmative</hi> judgement againſt us; your very <hi>ſeparating</hi> is a <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit</hi> and practical <hi>condemning</hi> of our Churches; if not as <hi>falſe,</hi> yet as <hi>impure; eouſque</hi> as that in ſuch Admiſtrations they cannot be by you, as Members commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated with, <hi>without ſin.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>However though we cannot communicate with you as Members of your <hi>particular</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, yet we will preſerve all <hi>Chriſtian Communion</hi> with you as Saints and Members of the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>This is as full a declining Communion with us as <hi>Churches,</hi> as if we were <hi>falſe</hi> Churches, <hi>p. 72.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <pb n="101" facs="tcp:58860:52"/>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>If this be called <hi>Schiſm,</hi> or the countenance of Schiſm, it is more then we have yet learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, either from the <hi>Scripture</hi> or any approved <hi>Author,</hi> p. 73.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>It gives manifeſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to <hi>perpetual Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſm,</hi> ſhould this be allowed you. Not that we think differences in <hi>Judgment</hi> in this or that point to be <hi>Schiſm,</hi> or that every <hi>Inconform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ty</hi> unto every thing is <hi>Schiſm,</hi> ſo as <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> be preſerved: Or that Separation from <hi>Idolotrous</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion <hi>ex ſe</hi> unlawful is <hi>Schiſm;</hi> but</p>
                     <p n="1">1. We find that you deſire not onely that you may be free from communicating <hi>as Members</hi> in thoſe <hi>Pariſhes</hi> where you dwell, but alſo that you may have <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to have Congregations of ſuch perſons, who out of <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> cannot communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58860:53"/> with us, but do <hi>voluntarily</hi> offer themſelves to joyn in <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> Congregations of <hi>another Communion.</hi> Which Seceſſion of our Members from us is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt <hi>rupture</hi> of our Societies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other, and is therefore a <hi>Schiſm in the body.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And if the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth call thoſe <hi>Diviſions</hi> of the Church, wherein Chriſtians did <hi>not</hi> ſeparate into diverſe <hi>formed Congregations</hi> of ſeveral Communions in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, <hi>Schiſms;</hi> much more may <hi>ſuch</hi> Separations as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire be ſo called.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We find it not alleaged as a <hi>Cauſe</hi> of your Separation, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that our Churches are <hi>falſe,</hi> or our Communion <hi>ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſe</hi> unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; but onely <hi>Scruple</hi> of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that you cannot without ſin as to you, partake in all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and enjoy all ordinances,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58860:53"/> which is no <hi>Cauſe</hi> of ſeparating; nor doth it take off <hi>Cauſleſs Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> from being <hi>Schiſm,</hi> which may ariſe from <hi>errours of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> as well as <hi>carnal</hi> and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <hi>Reaſons.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore we conceive the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of Separation muſt be ſhewn to be ſuch, as <hi>ex Natura rei</hi> will bear it out; which hath not <hi>yet</hi> been done, nor we think can be.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And now we deſire you to ſhew out of <hi>Scripture</hi> and approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Authors,</hi> what you have learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed concerning <hi>Schiſm:</hi> For the breaking off Members from their Churches which are <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully conſtituted Churches:</hi> and from Communion in Ordinances diſpenfed according to <hi>Gods word,</hi> without <hi>juſt</hi> and ſufficient <hi>Cauſe ex natura rei</hi> to juſtifie ſuch Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, and to joyn in other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58860:54"/> of <hi>ſeparate Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> either becauſe of <hi>Cauſleſs</hi> Scruple of their own Conſcience, or becauſe of <hi>perſonal</hi> failings in the <hi>Officers</hi> or <hi>Members</hi> of the Congregation from which they ſeparate, <hi>hath been accounted Schiſm,</hi> and the ſetting up <hi>Alta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re contra Altare.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And concurrently do <hi>approved Authors</hi> ſay, and we likewiſe conceive, that it is the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the Separation which gives both <hi>name</hi> and <hi>thing</hi> to <hi>Schiſm.</hi> For if the cauſe be <hi>unjuſt</hi> or inſufficient, according to the Rule of the <hi>Word</hi> of God, let our Brethren tell us what <hi>ſuch Separation</hi> is.</p>
                     <p>It is our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arneſt deſire and Prayer, that our Brethren might enjoy the Ordinances with the <hi>Peace</hi> of their <hi>Conſciences</hi> and of the <hi>Church</hi> alſo: or that they would rather deny themſelves of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58860:54"/> their <hi>full liberty</hi> in every point, then redeem it at the price of ſo much <hi>danger</hi> and diſq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>riet to the Churches of God, <hi>p.</hi> 74, 5, 6, 7.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>The <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Pariſh Churches are not ſuch as we can comfortably <hi>joyn</hi> with, and ſit down under.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presh.</speaker>
                     <p>We do not believe that you mean that onely ſuch ſhould be allowed to gather into <hi>your</hi> Congregations, who live under bad and <hi>unprofitable Miniſters,</hi> though that be the onely <hi>medium</hi> there uſed againſt our Reaſon.</p>
                     <p>Where the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> is without <note place="margin">P. 84, 85.</note> juſt exception, we refer it to your own <hi>Conſcinces,</hi> and to the practiſe of your <hi>Congregations,</hi> to ſay, how fit it is that the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſhould <hi>ordinarily,</hi> much leſs conſtantly, ſeek the Ordinances elſewhere.</p>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:58860:55"/>
                     <p>We long to know; what Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of our <hi>Pariſhes</hi> will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie your Conſciences; or how <hi>this Kingdom</hi> may be made the Kingdom of the <hi>Lord</hi> and of his Chriſt, better then by <hi>dividing</hi> it into ſeveral parts by the <hi>bounds</hi> of their <hi>dwellings:</hi> that all who give up their Names to Chriſt, may be <hi>taught</hi> and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, and have all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances adminiſtred among them <hi>ſuitable</hi> to their <hi>Conditions,</hi> p. 102.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>But it ſeems you would have us <hi>for ever</hi> to want the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> which is not to be endured, <hi>p.</hi> 102.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Why may not <hi>ſome expedient</hi> ſatisfie you in this, to prevent ſo great an evil as <hi>Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. We may <hi>not do evil for any good end.</hi> If a man ſhould be
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58860:55"/> brought to ſuch a <hi>Streight</hi> as that, either he muſt want the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> or <hi>ſeparate</hi> from the Congregation whereof he is a Member, he may here want the <hi>Ordinance</hi> (during this <hi>Errour</hi> of his Conſcience) with leſs danger, than to purchaſe it by a ſinful ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. This is a ſtrange and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous way of arguing, which may open a <hi>gap</hi> to as many <hi>Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> and Subdiviſions in the Church as the <hi>Errours</hi> are, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which the minds of men are ſubject. And if this be allow'd, we deſire you to conſider how long, not <hi>our</hi> Churches onely, but <hi>your own,</hi> or any other Churches in the World, ſhall be free from <hi>uncurable</hi> unquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>It muſt be a <hi>prejudice</hi> to the Church we are in, if we <hi>ſeparate</hi>
                        <pb n="108" facs="tcp:58860:56"/> from her in the Lords Supper: And yet you would have us live under their Government whom we prejudice, which ſeems unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to us, <hi>p.</hi>104.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>If your <hi>Errours</hi> cauſe prejudice againſt you, is it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable for you to be under the <hi>Government</hi> of that Church which is prejudiced by you? may you with good reaſon <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize</hi> the Church by <hi>Separation,</hi> and the Church have no reaſon to <hi>govern</hi> you; then <hi>prejudicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or ſcandalizing Errours are a <hi>Superſedeas to all Government?</hi> We do not then wonder that <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours</hi> and perverſe opinions ſo much <hi>abound;</hi> it may be, they are all but the <hi>mediums</hi> to <hi>liberty,</hi> and exemptions from <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>But living in a <hi>Pariſh,</hi> doth not make us <hi>Members</hi> of the Church.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <pb n="109" facs="tcp:58860:56"/>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>We grant it, a man muſt in order of <hi>Nature</hi> firſt be a Member of the <hi>Church viſible,</hi> and then living in a <hi>Pariſh,</hi> and making <hi>profeſſion</hi> of Chriſtianity, he may claim admiſſion into the Society of Chriſtians within thoſe <hi>bounds,</hi> and enjoy the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances which are there diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is your <hi>Chriſtian Charity?</hi> We would <hi>edifie</hi> our ſelves the beſt we can; and though we differ but in very <hi>ſmall</hi> matters, you will not ſuffer us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>Can you not be <hi>edified</hi> without <hi>Scandalizing</hi> the Church of God? we leave to all men to judge whoſe <hi>Charity</hi> is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt; theirs who labour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve <hi>union,</hi> or theirs who reſolve to <hi>ſeparate</hi> and break it? We think <hi>Charity</hi> binds Chriſtians to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58860:57"/> prevent all <hi>unjuſt</hi> and needleſs Separation. We wonder at your <hi>Charity,</hi> that coming ſo near us in <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>worſhip,</hi> nothing ſhould content you but a <hi>Separation,</hi> p. 105, 106.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>We cannot in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſet down, where we cannot enjoy <hi>all the Ordinances,</hi> p. 122.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. Have you <hi>all</hi> the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in <hi>your own</hi> Churches?</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Do you not hold <hi>ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> to be an Ordinance? have you theſe? Or be <hi>your</hi> Churches without ſome one ordinance, and not <hi>ours?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. To <hi>determine Controverſies of Faith,</hi> &amp; caſes of conſcience <hi>ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially,</hi> is an Ordinance: If you muſt be of no Church but where that is exerciſed, and the <hi>liberty</hi> of opinions <hi>reſtrained,</hi> your Churches would be ſoon deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And <hi>you</hi> would find it,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58860:57"/> we believe difficult to gather <hi>more.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>This would prove the beſt means of <hi>Uniformity</hi> and Conjunction, to allow us <hi>diſtinct Churches</hi> according to our own Principles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>This is a <hi>Riddle;</hi> we wonder how <hi>disjunction</hi> can be the only way of <hi>Conjunction,</hi> and <hi>Multiformity</hi> of <hi>Uniformity,</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> of <hi>Communion,</hi> and different Principles and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Conformity.</p>
                     <p>What Churches under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven may we not hold Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Uniformity, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with, upon <hi>ſuch terms? p.</hi> 123.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>But <hi>tender Conſciences</hi> ought to be relieved.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>We deſire to know whether every Perſons bare <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>lleadging</hi> tenderneſs of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58860:58"/> ſhall be ſufficient to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant his <hi>deſerting</hi> our Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>p.</hi> 49.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We much doubt, whether ſuch <hi>tenderneſs</hi> as ariſeth out of an op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nion, <hi>oui poteſt ſubeſſe falſum;</hi> when the Conſcience is ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that it may alſo be an <hi>erring</hi> Conſcience, can be a ſufficient ground to juſtifie ſuch material Separation, as our Brethren plead for. For though it may bind to <hi>forbear</hi> or ſuſpend the Act of Communion in that <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulur,</hi> wherein men conceive they cannot hold Communion without ſin; yet, it doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> bind to follow ſuch a <hi>poſitiv</hi> preſcript, as poſſibly may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe from the <hi>Will</hi> and Counſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of <hi>God:</hi> Of which kind w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> conceive this of <hi>gathering ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Churches</hi> out of other tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Churches to be one, <hi>p.</hi> 51.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58860:58"/>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>In caſe the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> be not adminiſtred in <hi>parity,</hi> a <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>emoval</hi> is allowed <hi>ordinarily:</hi> Now we would only gather our ſelves into other Churches; for <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>urer</hi> enjoyment, as to our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ciencis,</hi> of all ordinances, <hi>p.</hi> 50, 51.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>We conceive, the ground of your Separation from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne Church and gathering o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hers, to this end, that you may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e preſerved from ſinning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gainſt your <hi>Conſcie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ces;</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or the <hi>purer</hi> enjoyment of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inances, may to men of other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udgments be a ground to crave <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oleration</hi> for ſeparating from Churches which are <hi>pure,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>athering <hi>impure</hi> and corrupt Churches out of them, <hi>p.</hi> 50.</p>
                     <p>It was never the meaning of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he <hi>Aſſemblies</hi> to leave the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ent of <hi>pure</hi> or impure <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi>
                        <pb n="114" facs="tcp:58860:59"/> to this Caſe, unto the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone diſcretion of a <hi>particular</hi> Perſon: But before any leave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Parochial</hi> Congregation, ordinarily he ought to declare the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of his grievance, that if it may be his removal may be <hi>prevented:</hi> Except he think fit to change <hi>his dwelling;</hi> in which Caſe his removal is <hi>without offence.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhy may it not be as lawful to go to a <hi>ſeparate</hi> Congregation for relief, as to <hi>remove</hi> our dwelling to another <hi>Pariſh?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>It is one thing to remove to a Congregation which is under the <hi>ſame Rule;</hi> another, to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of a <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>fferent conſtitution</hi> from the Rule. In the one a ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>retains</hi> his Memberſhip; in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he <hi>renounceth</hi> it, <hi>p.</hi> 52.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <pb n="115" facs="tcp:58860:59"/>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>If the <hi>pureſt</hi> Churches in the VVorld, unto our Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in all <hi>other</hi> reſpects, ſhould impoſe as a condition in the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> of the Lords Supper any one thing that ſuch tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences cannot Joyn in (as ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>kneeling)</hi> if they remove from theſe Churches, and have <hi>liberty</hi> from the <hi>State</hi> to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into other Churches, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy this and other Ordinances, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>here is no <hi>Separation</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. If a Church require that which is <hi>evil</hi> of any Member, he muſt forbear to do it; yet, without <hi>Separation;</hi> and waite on Gods <hi>Providence</hi> in the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of that Church, till all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies have been tryed.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. He that is in this kind op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, may be relieved by <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal,</hi> or change his <hi>dwelling.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="116" facs="tcp:58860:60"/>3. They who thought <hi>kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the Act of Communion to be <hi>unlawful,</hi> either in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Scotland</hi> did <hi>ſeparate</hi> or renounce Memberſhip; but did ſome of them with <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Lear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend</hi> our Churches againſt thoſe of the <hi>Separation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>But, we hope you will not queſtion us, if we have <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> from the <hi>State</hi> to gather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other Churches.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>The Nature of Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is not to be meaſured by <hi>civil Acts</hi> or State, but by the <hi>Word</hi> of God: what notion you have of it we know not; but ſurely to leave all <hi>ordinary</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in any Church with <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſlike,</hi> when <hi>oppoſition</hi> or <hi>offence</hi> offers it ſelf, is to ſeparate from ſuch a Church in the <hi>Scripture;</hi> ſince ſuch a Separation was not in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> times, unleſs it
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58860:60"/> were uſed by <hi>falſe Teachers;</hi> all who profeſſed Chriſtianity held Communion together, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>differences</hi> of Judgment or <hi>Corruptions</hi> in practiſe, <hi>p.</hi> 55.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>Our Churches cannot be thought to be guilty of a plain and <hi>total Separation,</hi> unleſs we did wholly in all things differ, by ſetting up altogether <hi>differing Rules</hi> of Conſtitution, VVorſhip and Government.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>Of this Aſſertion we expect ſome proof: We read not the like in any <hi>Author antient</hi> or <hi>modern.</hi> Under this pretenſe <hi>Novatians, Donatiſts,</hi> all that ever were thought to <hi>ſeparate,</hi> may ſhelter themſelves; who them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, boaſting of their Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (the moſt rigid Separatiſts) hold the ſame Rule of worſhip and government for ſubſtance with you.</p>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:58860:61"/>
                     <p>We deſire you to conſider if every ſmall and <hi>circumſtantial</hi> difference amongſt thoſe who agree in moſt things, and thoſe moſt <hi>ſubſtantial,</hi> ſhall be a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground to gather Churches out of Churches into a ſeparate and diſtinct Communion, how the Churches of God ſhall ever be kept free from <hi>Rents</hi> and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, and how the <hi>Peace</hi> thereof is poſſible to be preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>But as we hold your Churches to be true Churches, ſo we are ready to hold <hi>occaſional</hi> Communion with them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p n="1">1. You have eſtranged your ſelves from us <hi>hitherto,</hi> and we have reaſon to queſtion, in what <hi>ſenſe</hi> you account our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Churches <hi>true.</hi> 2. If you may <hi>occaſionally</hi> exerciſe Acts of Communion with us
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:58860:61"/> once, a ſecond, a third time, without ſin; we know no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why it may not be <hi>ordinarily</hi> without ſin: And then Separation and gathering Churches would have been <hi>need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To ſeparate from thoſe Churches <hi>ordinarily</hi> and viſibly, with whom <hi>occaſionally</hi> you may Joyn without ſin, ſeemeth to be a moſt <hi>unjuſt</hi> Separation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>Suppoſe you do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count our gathering Churches <hi>ſinful,</hi> may not ſome things be <hi>tolerated</hi> which are thought <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>Our Reaſon againſt <hi>Toleration</hi> is not ſounded upon the Suppoſition that nothing <hi>unlawful</hi> may be tolerated; but upon the ſuppoſition of unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to tolerate the <hi>gathering Churches</hi> out of true Churches.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58860:62"/> And you do not once endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prove, either that ſuch <hi>gathering,</hi> or the <hi>tolerating</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is lawful.</p>
                     <p>We are to debate the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of <hi>forbearance,</hi> and may inſiſt upon any proper <hi>medium,</hi> to that end; for clearing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the lawfulneſs or unlawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that point of <hi>Church gathering</hi> is one of the moſt <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsary.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>If we do not gather into other Churches; <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes</hi> that cannot conform muſt live without <hi>ſome Ordinances</hi> all their dayes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Of this before; but we anſwer, that</hi> you wave the main buſineſs, <hi>viz.</hi> whether there be any <hi>Example</hi> in Gods Word for gathering Churches out of Churches.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="121" facs="tcp:58860:62"/>1. This opens a <hi>gap</hi> for all <hi>Sects</hi> to challenge the ſame <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> as their due. It ſhould be conſidered.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Whether we muſt follow an <hi>Erroneous Conſcience</hi> ſo far as to gather into <hi>new</hi> Churches.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Whether this be not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by the Churches in <hi>New-England.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>Is it not the <hi>Right</hi> of every man to <hi>chooſe</hi> his own <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>Certainly ſome would deny it, and it will be like to breed much <hi>confuſion.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the tolerated will have the greateſt <hi>priviledge</hi> by it; they ſhall enjoy it <hi>abſolutely,</hi> when thoſe under the <hi>Rule</hi> cannot, without removing their <hi>dwellings,</hi> p. 64, 65.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>Though we do ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, we are ſuch as have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58860:63"/> 
                        <hi>good Teſtimony of our Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Peaceableneſs:</hi> And we did not ſeparate till we had uſed <hi>all means</hi> in faithfulneſs to know the mind of Chriſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>We ſhall not mind you how <hi>Teſtimonies of Godlineſs</hi> are not always infallible Protections againſt <hi>Schiſm</hi> or <hi>Hereſie;</hi> as in <hi>Mileſius, Lucifer, Audaeus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>We conceive that amongſt other means uſed in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, this ſhould be one; that each perſon give an account of his <hi>Scruple</hi> to the Elderſhip or Congregation where he dwells; that ſo he may either receive ſatisfaction, or have from them a Teſtimony of Godlineſs and Peaceableneſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>But you uncharitably charge us with the guilt of Schiſm, though we do not ſay your Churches are falſe and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58860:63"/> not to be communicated with, which is hard meaſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>We have anſwered this already, but further we ſay;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit <hi>Schiſm</hi> conſiſts not in every diverſity of <hi>opinion</hi> or <hi>practice,</hi> but in an open <hi>breach</hi> of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an love; yet we ſee not how you can acquit your ſelves even by <hi>this Rule;</hi> when you openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs a neceſſity to <hi>recede</hi> from our Churches as <hi>Members,</hi> which while yet you acknowledge them to be true Churches of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Thus to depart from true Churches, is not to hold Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them <hi>as ſuch;</hi> but rather by <hi>departing,</hi> to declare them to <hi>be ſuch:</hi> Surely at beſt we may ſay of this courſe as the Philoſopher did of the <hi>Mileſians, Mileſii quidem non ſunt inſipientes, ea tamen agunt quae inſipientes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:58860:64"/>
                     <p>Mark once for all, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aptly the <hi>Reflecter</hi> would make all the ſtreſs of the Presbyterians Argument, to prove the Schiſm of the Independents, to beat upon the <hi>endeavours</hi> of their Churches to <hi>reform:</hi> For the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents were as unſatisfied with <hi>their Reformation,</hi> as they are with their worſhip. For they ſay plainly, the <hi>Reformation which the Aſſembly hath ultimately pitch'd upon ſatisfies not our Conſciences, as our Brethren know.</hi> No, you every where find, they charge them with Separation from true Churches, and aggravate that charge from <hi>their acknowledgment</hi> of the truth of thoſe Churches from which they ſeparate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Indep.</speaker>
                     <p>But you endeavour our diſgrace, and caſt an <hi>odium</hi> upon us by the word <hi>Schiſm.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Presb.</speaker>
                     <p>Your way would give
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58860:64"/> countenance to a <hi>perpetual Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in the Church, ſtill drawing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Churches under the <hi>Rule:</hi> And <hi>Schiſm</hi> differs no more from <hi>Diviſion,</hi> then <hi>Greek</hi> from <hi>Latine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We deſire you, that by aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of Conſcience to your <hi>diſſenting</hi> from the Rule <hi>and eſtabliſhment</hi> of a <hi>Church-way</hi> or <hi>Church-order</hi> to your way and godly party, you would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect an <hi>odium</hi> upon us or the Churches under the <hi>Rule.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>You know that to give counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to an unjuſt or <hi>cauſleſs</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from a lawful Church-Communion, is not far from gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving countenance to <hi>Schiſm:</hi> Eſpecially wheen the grounds, upon which this <hi>Separation</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, are <hi>ſuch,</hi> as upon which all other <hi>poſſible ſcruples</hi> may claim a like Indulgence, and ſo this <hi>Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi>
                        <pb n="126" facs="tcp:58860:65"/> being the <hi>firſt,</hi> ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but lay a Foundation, and open the Gap, whereat as <hi>many Diviſions</hi> in the Church, as there be <hi>Scruples</hi> in the minds of men, ſhall upon the ſelf ſame equity be let in, <hi>p.</hi> 66.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:58860:65"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Concluſion, with a</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulation.</head>
                  <p>OUR work, we ſee, was ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually done to our hands many years agon, both againſt the <hi>Independents</hi> and the <hi>preſent Presbyterians:</hi> whoſe practice in <hi>gathering Churches,</hi> and whoſe <hi>Arguments</hi> in defence of that practice are very much the ſame. And <hi>both</hi> are here abundantly confuted by theſe <hi>Presbyterian</hi> weighty Reaſons: Which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed are ſuch, as took not their ſtrength from any peculiar <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions</hi> of the times when they were written; but are <hi>now,</hi> and ever will be of <hi>equal</hi> and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible prevalency.</p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:58860:66"/>
                  <p>Therefore the <hi>Dialogue</hi> is as proper and ſeaſonable <hi>now,</hi> as thoſe <hi>Papers</hi> were <hi>then:</hi> Do but change the <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>name</hi> [Presbyterian] for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the whole is as <hi>pertinent</hi> to our <hi>preſent</hi> State as the Reader can wiſh. And indeed, what can the wit of the preſent <hi>diſsenters</hi> add <hi>new,</hi> to the Argument as it was then managed? Or what have they ſaid more for themſelves? <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veiw</hi> and judge.</p>
                  <div type="list">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The</hi> Independents <hi>then pleaded.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. WE onely deſire a <hi>liberty</hi> to worſhip God in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of our own diſtinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> from the <hi>Parochial.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. We condemn not the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial</hi> Churches as falſe.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <pb n="129" facs="tcp:58860:66"/>3. We differ from you onely in ſmall matters.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. We agree with you as to the ſubſtance of Doctrine and worſhip.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Yet we cannot joyn with you in all things without ſin.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. And we cannot live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any one ordinance.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Therefore we joyn in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Congregation only for the enjoyment of all ordinances for our ſpiritual good.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Yet we will preſerve. all Chriſtian Communion with the Saints in the Church Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. We cannot be Members of that Congregation where our dwelling is.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. However we will hold oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional Communion with you.</p>
                     <p n="11">
                        <pb n="103" facs="tcp:58860:67"/>11. This is no Schiſm, or countenance of Schiſm, or rigid ſeparation.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. We cannot approve or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie by the Pariſh Miniſters.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. 'Tis the priviledge of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one to chooſe his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Living in a Pariſh doth not make Members of a Church.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Removal from one Pariſh to another is allowed, and why not to a ſeparate Cogregation?</p>
                     <p n="16">16. Tender Conſciences ought thus to be relieved.</p>
                     <p n="17">17. It is againſt Chriſtian charity to deny this liberty.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. This Liberty will prove the beſt means of Uniformity.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. What if we have liberty from the State to gather Churches?</p>
                     <p n="20">20. Some things may be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated that are thought unlawful.</p>
                     <p n="21">
                        <pb n="131" facs="tcp:58860:67"/>21. Multitudes that cannot conform, muſt live without ſome ordinances all their days.</p>
                     <p n="22">22. Thoſe that ſeparate have given good Teſtimony of their Godlineſs and Peaceableneſs: And have uſed all means firſt to know the mind of Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="23">23. You charge us with Schiſm to render us odious.</p>
                     <p>All <hi>theſe</hi> were <hi>Independent</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments in 1644. how they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſed to be <hi>Presbyterian</hi> in 1672. I know not: But this I know that <hi>then</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> were not ſhy to declare <hi>gathering Churches out of our Churches</hi> under all flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes and iittle pretenſes, was a <hi>Schiſmatical</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, and not to be <hi>allowed.</hi> For which, they gave the world, not onely their <hi>Authority,</hi>
                        <pb n="132" facs="tcp:58860:68"/> but ſuch <hi>Reaſons</hi> as you have <hi>heard,</hi> but ſhall never <hi>ſee anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> Some of their Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons follow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Some of the Presbyterian Aſserti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby they refelled the foreſaid Independent pretenſes for gathering Churches (as more at large appeareth in the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue) are theſe.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. OUr Parochial Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations are true Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To make one a Member of ſuch a Church, it is ſufficient that he <hi>profeſseth Chriſtianity, and lives in the Pariſh,</hi> and he may claim Communion thereupon.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The old Non-Conformiſts did not ſeparate from the <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> or renounce Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58860:68"/> though they thought <hi>kneeling</hi> at the Communion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful (and I may add, had as much cauſe to complain of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,</hi> and want of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as any have now) but did ſome of them with Zeal and Learning defend our Churches againſt thoſe of the <hi>Separation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. None ought to be indulg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but ſuch as agree with the eſtabliſhment as to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. Theſe ſhould not be indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſo far, as to ſeparate and gather new Churches.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. This is <hi>Schiſm,</hi> and the means of confuſion in the Church and in Families.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. None are to be allowed to withdraw Communion in things wherein they <hi>agree</hi> with us: But in all <hi>ſuch</hi> things they ought to
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:58860:69"/> retain Communion with the Congregation <hi>where they live.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8. The Separatiſts holding our Churches to be <hi>true</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, is an <hi>Aggravation</hi> of their Separation.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. To depart from Churches me acknowledg to be <hi>true,</hi> is not to hold Communion with them as <hi>ſuch;</hi> but rather by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, to declare them <hi>not</hi> to be ſuch.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. To leave all <hi>Ordinary</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in any Church with <hi>Diſlike,</hi> when <hi>Oppoſition</hi> or <hi>Offence</hi> offers it ſelf; is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o Separate in the <hi>Scripture-</hi>Senſe, and was not in being in the Apoſtles times, unleſs by <hi>falſe</hi> Teachers.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. All who profeſſed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity in the Apoſtles times, held Communion together, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding differences in <hi>Judgment,</hi> or corruptions in <hi>Practice.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="12">
                        <pb n="135" facs="tcp:58860:69"/>12. The Judgment of pure and impure Ordinances, is not to be left to the <hi>alone diſcretion</hi> of a particular Perſon.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. To Separate from thoſe Churches <hi>Ordinarily</hi> and Viſibly, with whom <hi>occaſionally</hi> you may joyn without Sin, ſeemeth to be a moſt unjuſt Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. It is one thing to Remove to a Congregation that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame <hi>Rule;</hi> another, to a Congregation of a <hi>different</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. In the one, a man retaineth his Memberſhip, in the other he <hi>Renounceth</hi> it.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. <hi>Teſtimonies of Godlineſs</hi> are no infallible Protections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Schiſm.</p>
                     <p n="16">16. 'Tis no breach of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to hinder all unjuſt Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions.</p>
                     <p n="17">
                        <pb n="136" facs="tcp:58860:70"/>17. A man may want the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> with leſs Danger, then to purchaſe it by a ſinful Separation.</p>
                     <p n="18">18. The Church is not bound to Indulge a Liberty to <hi>Erring</hi> Conſciences, eſpecially to the evident diſturbance of her own Peace.</p>
                     <p n="19">19. No pretences of tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Conſciences,</hi> or of <hi>Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication,</hi> or of enjoying all <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> or of holding Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with us as <hi>Saints</hi> in the Church <hi>Catholick,</hi> or of <hi>Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal</hi> Communion with us as a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, or of holding communion with us <hi>as far as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>re able,</hi> or that they cannot joyn with us <hi>without Sin,</hi> or laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, no acceptions that they take either againſt our <hi>Officers</hi> or <hi>Members:</hi> None of theſe, or
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:58860:70"/> any ſuch, can warrant a <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration</hi> from us, or gathering new Churches out of ours. For theſe make not the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of a juſt ſeparation, which ought to appear <hi>ex natura rei.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rememmber from whence thou art faln.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>PAge 33. Line 2. Read, <hi>Not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcence ſake,</hi> Rom. 13. 5. p. 34. l. 14. dele <hi>and.</hi> p. 35. l. 18. r. <hi>things.</hi> p. 40. l. 1. r. <hi>Subterfuges.</hi> p. 54. l. 21. r. <hi>ſhould not be.</hi> p. 78. l. 17. r. <hi>our Government.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:58860:71"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Some Books Printed for and ſold by</hi> James Collins <hi>at the</hi> Kings Arms <hi>in</hi> Ludgate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet, 1673.</head>
                  <p>OBſervations upon Military and Political Affairs, by the moſt Honourable <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle:</hi> Folio, <hi>price</hi> 6. s.</p>
                  <p>A Sermon Preached by <hi>Seth</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> at the Funeral of the moſt Honourable <hi>George</hi> Duke of <hi>Albemarle:</hi> Quarto, <hi>price</hi> 6. d.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Philoſophia Pia,</hi> or, A Diſcourſe of the Religious tendences of the Experimental Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, to which is added a Recommendation and Defence of Reaſon in the Affairs of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by <hi>Joſeph Glanvil,</hi> Rector of <hi>Bath:</hi> Octavo, <hi>price</hi> 2 s.</p>
                  <p>The Way to Happineſs repreſented in its Difficulties and Encouragemeents; and cleared from many popular and dangerous miſtakes, by <hi>Joſeph Glanvil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Praefatory Anſwer to <hi>Mr. Henry Stubbs,</hi> the Doctor of <hi>Warwick,</hi> by <hi>Joſ. Glanvil:</hi> Octavo, <hi>price</hi> 1. s. 6. d.</p>
                  <p>The Life and Death of <hi>Mr. George Herbert,</hi> the Excellent Author of the Divine Poems. Written by <hi>Iſ. Walton:</hi> Octavo, <hi>price</hi> 1. s.</p>
                  <p>A Diſcourſe of the Forbearance or pena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb facs="tcp:58860:71"/> which a due Reformation requires; by <hi>Herbert Thorndike</hi> one of the Prebendaries o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Weſtminster:</hi> Octavo.</p>
                  <p>A Private Conference between a rich Alder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man, and a poor Country Vicar made Publick wherein is diſcourſed the Obligation of Oaths, which have been impoſed on the Subjects of <hi>England:</hi> Octavo. 2. s.</p>
                  <p>The Epiſcopacy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> juſtified to be Apoſtolical from the Authority of the Primitive Church: and from the confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the moſt famous Divines beyond the Seas, by the Right Reverend the late Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Dureſm,</hi> with a Preface written by Sir <hi>Henry Yelverton</hi> Baronet: Octavo.</p>
                  <p>A Collection of Sermons preached before the King at <hi>White-hall</hi> by the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Seth</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Catholick Charity recommended in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon before the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> in order to the abating the animoſities among Chriſtians that have been oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by differences in Religion, by <hi>Joſ. Glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile,</hi> Rector of <hi>Bath, price</hi> 6. d.</p>
                  <p>A Mirrour of Chriſtianity, and a Miracle of Charity; or an exact Narrative of the Life and Death of the Lady <hi>Alice</hi> Dutches <hi>Dudley,</hi> by <hi>R. Coreman,</hi> D. D. <hi>price</hi> 6 d.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58860:72"/>
                  <p>The General Aſſembly, or the neceſſity of the receiving the Communion in our Publique Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations evinced from the Nature of the Church, the Word of God, and Presbyterian Principles; A Sermon by <hi>Francis Fulwood,</hi> D. D. <hi>price</hi> 6. d.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Miſerere Cleri;</hi> A Sermon preſenting the Miſeries of the Clergy, and Aſſigning their true Cauſes in order to Redreſs, by <hi>Edw. Wettenhall,</hi> B. D. <hi>price</hi> 6. d.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim &amp; Thummim;</hi> or the Clergies Dignity and Duty recommended in a Viſitation Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; by <hi>Mal. Convant,</hi> B. D. <hi>price</hi> 6. d.</p>
                  <p>A Diſcourſe of Toleration, in anſwer to a late Book, entituled, A Diſcourſe of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of <hi>England, price</hi> 6. d.</p>
                  <p>Indulgence not juſtified, being a Continuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Diſcourſe of Toleration, in anſwer to the Arguments of a late Book, entituled, A Peace-Offering or Plea for Indulgence; and to another, call'd, The ſecond Diſcourſe of the Religion of <hi>England, price</hi> 6 d.</p>
                  <p>Toleration not to be abus'd, or a ſerious Queſtion ſoberly debated and reſolved upon Presbyterian Principles, <hi>&amp;c. price</hi> 6 d.</p>
                  <p>The Judgment of the Learned and Pious St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> concerning Penal Laws againſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, and for Unity in Religion, delivered in his 48 Epiſtle to <hi>Vincentius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:58860:72"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
